<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christs counsell to his languishing church of Sardis. Or, The dying or decaying Christian, with the meanes and helpes of his recovery and strengthening. By Obadiah Sedgwicke, B. of D. late preacher to the inhabitants of S. Mildreds Bredstreet, London</title>
            <author>Sedgwick, Obadiah, 1600?-1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 196 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 142 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11850</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22151</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117037</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852252</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852252</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17566</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11850)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17566)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1362:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christs counsell to his languishing church of Sardis. Or, The dying or decaying Christian, with the meanes and helpes of his recovery and strengthening. By Obadiah Sedgwicke, B. of D. late preacher to the inhabitants of S. Mildreds Bredstreet, London</title>
                  <author>Sedgwick, Obadiah, 1600?-1658.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 262, [10] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T[homas] B[adger] for L. Fawne, and S. Gellibrand, at the brasen Serpent in S. Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1640.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Includes index.</note>
                  <note>With a final errata leaf; the last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17566:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17566:1"/>
            <p>CHRISTS Counſell to his lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing Church of SARDIS. <hi>OR,</hi> The dying or decaying Chriſtian, with the meanes and helpes of his recovery and ſtrengthening.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> OBADIAH SEDGWICKE, B. of D. late Preacher to the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of S. <hi>Mildreds Bredſtreet, London</hi> 
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, </p>
               <bibl>2 Tim. 1. 6.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Frustra velociter currit, qui prius quam ad metas vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit deficit,</hi> 
               </p>
               <bibl>Greg. mor. l. 2. c. 40.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. B.</hi> for L. FAWNE, and S. GELLIBRAND, at the braſen Serpent in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1640.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17566:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17566:2"/>
            <head>To the right Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, Captaine <hi>Nicholas Criſpe</hi> Eſquire, and Miſtreſſe <hi>Anne Criſpe</hi> his pious conſort, To Maſter <hi>Samuel Criſpe,</hi> and Miſtreſſe <hi>Katharine</hi> his vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous wife, with all the reſt of the Pariſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners, my loving friends, the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants in Saint <hi>Mildreds, Bredſtreet.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My deare and worthy friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Aint <hi>Bernard</hi> with a very apt phraſe, anſwered a ſpeciall friend of his, challenging of him in the ſtreines of affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, thus, <hi>O ſcrutans renes
<pb facs="tcp:17566:3"/> et corda Deus, &amp;c. quòd diligam illum ex dono tuo &amp; ſuo merito, tu ſcis &amp; ego ſentio, quatenus autem diligam, tu ſcis, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go neſcio,</hi> (that is) Oh Lord, thou who knoweſt and ſearcheſt the inmoſt cloſets of the heart, that I love my friend, thou knoweſt it, and I know it: how much I love him thou doeſt know, but I doe not know. The ſame I apply to my ſelfe and all of you; if ſuſpecting my affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to you, becauſe of my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting
<pb facs="tcp:17566:3"/> from you, Lord, thou who knoweſt all things, thou knoweſt that I love them, and I know it, how much thou onely knoweſt, but I cannot expreſſe.</p>
            <p>You were a people (of all that hitherto I have lived with, and of all that ever I preached unto) of the moſt generall union with your ſelves, and of the moſt liberal and unwearied affection to your Miniſter; the maine ſcruple many times to mee, was, leſt divers of you ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:17566:4"/> out-ſtretch your meaſures.</p>
            <p>All the reſpects which you owed and ſhewed to my Miniſtery, and all the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements which you heaped on my ſelfe, I doe now the ſecond time publike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acknowledge: and as my thankfulneſſe preſents it ſelf to you all, ſo in ſpeciall man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to you, much honoured Captaine, and your worthy wife, by whoſe good opinion and affection I was (through Gods mercy) brought unto that place: you have ſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced
<pb facs="tcp:17566:4"/> your favours both to my ſelfe and ſome friends of mine, that I doe moſt gladly embrace this preſent occaſion of publike testimony and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement; not that it is ſufficient to cleare all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, but onely that you may know, kindeneſſes long ſince given, are never loſt in a thankefull breaſt.</p>
            <p>My deſire for you all is, that ye may be ſaved, and my deſire to you all is, that yee would ſeriouſly anſwer the many precious and heavenly
<pb facs="tcp:17566:5"/> opportunities of Gods grace; it is not onely a vanity, but a danger, a danger both ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame and ſure, to dally with our ſoules: God hath ſowne much ſeed by many of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants among you, and beleeve me, he expects an harveſt, wee cannot anſwer great meanes with great ſinfulneſſe or little goodneſſe. To whom any thing is given, of them ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is required, (even the man of one talent was made accountable) but to whom much is given, of them much
<pb facs="tcp:17566:5"/> ſhall be required. My deare friends if ye be wiſe, be wiſe for your ſelves, be good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed. You honour our miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and provide well for your owne eternall good; when you goe into an holy way, and goe on in that way, the ſight is incongruous, and the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count will be ſad, when Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters doctrines are very heavenly, and peoples con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation are very earthly and ſinfull; a melting heaven and a hardned earth meet ill. At length let us ſee our ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
<pb facs="tcp:17566:6"/> and pains in your lives; we preach and dye, and men heare and dye; we preach out our health, our ſtrength, our lives; Oh that our hearers would take pitty on us, and mend their hearts and waies. If we boaſt that our meanes are greater then others, wee muſt tremble alſo to thinke if our accounts, before God ſhould prove worſe then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>Therefore for your parts, as you have begun, ſo with all alacrity and industry, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue
<pb facs="tcp:17566:6"/> and perſevere. Our life is ſhort, duties many, worke daily, and reward ſure and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. An eternity with God ſhould make us good, and keepe us doing, and hold us faithfull, and make us fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. To the everlasting arms of his protection, and to the perpetuall influences of his grace and mercy in Chriſt, he commends you all, who is, to you all,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your much obliged and affectionate friend, OBADIAH SEDGWICKE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:17566:7"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F thou expecteſt in this Treatiſe what is curious and branched over with art, ſpare thine eye any further travell, it is not here<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> divine doctrines ſerve rather for the ſtomacke then the palate. In preaching theſe Sermons, I followed Saint <hi>Cyprians</hi> directions to <hi>Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> to make choiſe not of <hi>Diſerta,</hi> but <hi>Fortia,</hi> I looked very little at harmony which might take the eare, but moſt of all at energy, which might reach the conſcience.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17566:7"/>
            <p>I know well that there is a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and ſeaſonable uſe of learning, I am not of his minde who would have Preachers ſtudy no booke but the Bible; onely this, Miniſters (if I miſtake not) muſt conſider their auditors, and then and there, uſe their choiſer learning, when and where it may not amaze, but profit; when all is ſummed up, this will be found the moſt comfortable truth, no Preacher is ſo learned, as he who can ſaue ſoules.</p>
            <p>And now if thou pleaſeſt, reade the worke, and receiue this counſell from me; aboue all, ſtriue for ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall life (it is thy greateſt honour to be good) and when thou haſt obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it, take heed of dying, the dead man and the dying Chriſtian, are
<pb facs="tcp:17566:8"/> two ſad ſights; it is wofull either to be a brand falling into hell, or to be a ſtar falling downe from heauen: the riſing ſunne is more and more beautifull, but the waining moone is more full of ſpots and darkeneſse: though all may not be loſt, yet his ſhipwrackes are high who hath loſt much in his jewels, and almoſt all in his comforts: no more but this, keepe heauenly things as thou wouldeſt keepe heauen it ſelfe.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in any ſpirituall furtherance, OBADIAH SEDGWICKE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17566:8"/>
            <head>CHRISTS COVNSELL to His languiſhing CHURCH.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>REVEL. 3. 2, 3 verſes.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>Be watchfull and ſtrengthen the things that remaine, which are ready to dye, for I have not found thy works perfect before God.</p>
                  <p>Remember therefore how thou haſt recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and heard, and hold faſt and repent, &amp;c.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He author of this Booke was IESUS CHRIST; the pen-man was <hi>Iohn</hi> the Apoſtle, the matter of it, is
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17566:9"/> generally myſterious; the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whom it concernes are the ſeven Churches in <hi>Aſia,</hi> but the ſcope of it extends to all the Churches, ſucceeding the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles to the end of the world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Epheſus</hi> (the firſt of theſe Churches) is taxed for apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie; <hi>Smyrna</hi> (the ſecond of them) is encouraged to conſtancie; <hi>Pergamus</hi> &amp; <hi>Thyatira</hi> (the third and fourth of them) are char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for permiſſion of ſome ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry; <hi>Sardis</hi> (the fifth of them) is deepely queſtioned for hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie; <hi>Philadelphia</hi> (the ſixth of them) is commended for fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and <hi>Laodicea</hi> (the laſt of them) is condemned for neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trality or indifferency.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:17566:9"/>
            <p>In this Epiſtle to <hi>Sardis,</hi> you have,</p>
            <p n="1">1 An inſcription: 1. To whom? unto the Angell of the Church in <hi>Sardis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 From whom? He that hath the ſeven ſpirits (<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) Chriſt, who hath manifold abundance of ſpirituall gifts and graces in his owne diſpoſing, and imparts them by his ſpirit.</p>
            <p>2 A deſcription of that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell and Church; what they were,</p>
            <p n="1">1 In ſemblance; Thou haſt a name that thou liveſt, <hi>q. d.</hi> ſo thou boaſteſt, and ſo others imagine that thou an furniſhed with vitals for doctrine and diſcipline.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:17566:10"/>2 In ſubſtance; but thou art dead, <hi>q. d.</hi> there is no ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, thy Gold is but Tinne, and thy piety but formality: the powers of truth and grace were extremely fainting &amp; languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and as it were expiring.</p>
            <p n="3">3 A direction of them what to doe, the which direction is,</p>
            <p n="1">1 Generall, <hi>Be watchfull or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake:</hi> no reformation without diligent and ſerious conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Speciall, where,</p>
            <p n="1">1 The matter of it, <hi>Streng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the things which remaine, that are ready to dye</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 The equity of it, <hi>for I have not found thy works perfect before God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:17566:10"/>3 The manner of perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of this direction expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in two particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1 In remembrance of the good truths, or rather of the manner how they once recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and heard them, amplified with a ſpeciall exhortation to hold them faſt,</p>
            <p n="2">2 In repentance of all evill, eſpecially of their hypocriſie and languor, <hi>(And repent.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The matter is ſo large which might be inſiſted on, as that I know not well where to pitch, I ſhall onely be able (as reapers doe in the full field) to cut down many particulars, and leave the binding of them up to ſome one more skilfull harveſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17566:11"/> man: take them thus.</p>
            <p n="1">1 That people living under evangelicall teaching, may yet be but in a decaying and dying condition <hi>(the things that be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to dye.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 That ſpirituals are to be ſuccoured and ſtrengthened if once they grow languiſhing and dying, <hi>(ſtrengthen the things that, &amp;c.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 That the eſtate, though viſibly faire to the eyes of men, yet it may be really imperfect in the eyes of God, <hi>[I have not found thy works perfect before God.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 A right remembrance and retention of originall truths, are the way to revive a dying
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17566:11"/> chriſtian, to fetch him againe. <hi>[Remember therefore, &amp;c.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>6 Spirituall decayings doe require ſpirituall repentings: <hi>[and repent.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I begin with the firſt of theſe, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> That people living under e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelicall teaching, may yet be but in a dying condition: for the opening of this aſſertion, premiſe with me theſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.
<note place="margin">Three things premiſed.</note>
            </p>
            <p>1 There are three ſorts of people who may live under the preaching of the word.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Some manifeſtly prophane, who are ſtarke dead, there is neither the ſubſtance, nor the ſemblance of any heavenly life in them.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:17566:12"/>2 Others are cunningly hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriticall, whoſe leafe of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion ſeemes to live, but ſecret core of corruption convinceth that they are dead.</p>
            <p n="3">3 A third ſort is of ſuch as are vitally good, there is a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall life truely implanted in them, and a profeſſion in ſome meaſure anſwerable thereunto.</p>
            <p>The propoſition I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand even of this latter ſort, that even theſe may be in a dying condition.</p>
            <p>a This dying diſpoſition properly conſiſts in a manifeſt decay of ſpirituall principles; for looke as when a man is dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a naturall way, the vitall principles of <hi>Calidum</hi> and <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midum</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:17566:12"/> are notoriouſly impair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; ſo when a Chriſtian is dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a ſpirituall way, thoſe principles of heavenly life within him, are exceedingly ſinking and failing, and decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: there is not that ſtrength, nor that activity, nor that aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duity in the ſpirit or heart of man, as formerly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> but he works man, as formerly, but he works weakely (like a dying pulſe) and <hi>cum laeſis facultatibus,</hi> as a man goes with lame legges, and a ſickly body, ſo he walkes with wounded principles and a lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing pining ſoule.</p>
            <p>3 But if you will have the point in a more ample manner, then know that a Chriſtian may be dying partly,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:17566:13"/>1 In profeſſion, his very <note place="margin">A Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian may be dying in ſeven things.</note> leaves may wither; that viſible forwardneſſe of zeale and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, that wonted preſence of his at the ordinances, they may admit of an extreme ſluggiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and remiſſeneſſe; he may grow a ſtranger to God.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In converſation: His hand may ſhrivell and diſflouriſh: that former aſſociation of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with the people of God, may now be no delight, and profitable diſcourſes of heaven and of holineſſe, may now be much laid aſide, there may now drop no ſuch waters from his fountaine, and very little good from his ſociety: his can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle may burne darkely, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17566:13"/> with a very imperfect and loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing light.</p>
            <p n="3">3 In affection, that flame of love and ſea of deſires, and <hi>Eden</hi> of delight, may like a great fire be reduced to a few coales and cinders: Chriſt puts the Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians in minde of their firſt love that it was left, <hi>Revelat.</hi> 2. 4. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Revel.</hi> 2. 4.</note> though not abſolutely for na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, yet eminently for meaſure, and S. <hi>Paul</hi> upbraideth the Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lathians for that ſtrange coole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in their affections to his perſon and miniſtery, whereas at the firſt, their zeale was ſo forward, as that their very eyes <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 15. were at his ſervice. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 15</note>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 In duties which may now be chopt off by intermiſſion, or
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17566:14"/> wrought out with voluntary diſtractions, either none, or rugged, done with a kinde of formality, coldly, chilly, care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly.</p>
            <p>Heretofore no time was too long, no diverſion ſufficiently excuſable, no praying ſatisfying without lamenting compun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and groanings of ſpirit, or without ſome more fervent violence and wreſtling with God.</p>
            <p>But now this and other du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are like a pulſe hardly felt; words ſuffice, and almoſt an <hi>opus operatum</hi> is enough.</p>
            <p n="5">5 In judgement, that whereas formerly the minde and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding were
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label>(like the Needle
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17566:14"/> looking to the Poleſtarre) with much admiration and delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion taken up with the medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of God and Chriſt, and divine truths and waies. Now vaine objects are doted upon poore, inferiour, tranſitory de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights and profits, take up the lodging, and ſo fill the ſoule, that it becomes almoſt a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to holy contemplations and meditations. It hath almoſt loſt the relliſh of the ſtudious thoughts of God, or Chriſt, or ſalvation.</p>
            <p n="6">6 In gifts or parts, which through too much indulgence to carnall eaſe or affectation of worldly greatneſſe or defect of fit imployment, may like a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17566:15"/> ſharpe ſword, grow ruſty, or like ſtanding waters in a poole, be almoſt drawne dry and empty.</p>
            <p n="7">7 But which is the maineſt and worſt of all, the Chriſtian may be dying in his very gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; as the health of man may admit of eclipſes, and the very life of man may admit of ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings and faintings, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> ſo the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry graces in a Chriſtian may be much checked and wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and impaired in their anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent degrees and acts.</p>
            <p>Partly through want of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe, partly by not admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring ſuccour &amp; ſtrength unto them by a conſtant application of the ordinances, partly by
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:17566:15"/> hearkning unto ſome ſinfull temptations.</p>
            <p>So that now repentance may become more difficult and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and godly ſorrow can ſcarce be diſcerned for that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame hardneſſe of heart, and faith can ſcarce finde the way, or make any uſe of Chriſt, and the promiſes, but the gates of unbeliefe ſeeme to poſſeſſe the ſoule.</p>
            <p>Yea, the feare of God may now not ſo reſtraine and awe, and the love of God may not ſo prevaile and excite, as they have done in former times.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>But you will demand what may be the cauſes of this dying condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi> 
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:17566:16"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> I conjecture theſe. </p>
            <p n="1">1 <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> Some deadly corruption which hath ſeized upon their ſpirits: if poyſon get into the body, it works upon the ſpirits, and ſo weakens and indangers life.</p>
            <p>The people of God are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times taſting of poyſon, they are tampering with unſound doctrines, which as they doe infect the judgement, ſo they doe abate their ſpirituall prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and abilities. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle was afraid that he had loſt his labour, and ſpent himſelfe in vaine to thoſe of <hi>Galatia,</hi> that they were even leaving their hold in Chriſt, and what was the cauſe of it? Surely ſome
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17566:16"/> falſe Apoſtles had leavened them with errour about cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, and the obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the law. When the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is corrupted with any er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, then truths are not of that power with the ſoule, &amp; where truth looſeth in authority, there grace will looſe in its ſtrength and efficacie.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Some deadly wound is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto them; you know that a man may dye, not onely by a draught of poyſon, but <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by the cut of a ſword, which divides the parts, and lets out the bloud that carries and preſerves the life of man.</p>
            <p>There are things which doe fight againſt the ſoul, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 11. <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 11.</note>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:17566:17"/> and not onely fight againſt it, but wound it; nay not the ſoule and conſcience onely, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe our very graces.</p>
            <p>Sinnings doe not onely prove a troubleſome wound to the conſcience, but likewiſe a kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and dying wound to our graces; if any thing in the world extinguiſheth or abateth our graces, they are our ſinnings, which are to graces as water to the fire. But now even the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God doe many times hearken to ſome baſer luſts and viler commiſſions (as you know in <hi>David</hi> and others) and when ſinne hath got any favour in the judgement or affection, it is like a diſeaſe which will not
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:17566:17"/> off without a manifeſt breach of health and ſtrength;
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> ſinne lames our graces.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Some deadly neglect; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> if the ſoule grow negligent, it will quickly grow dying, as you ſhal ſee that inordinate abſtinence and neglect of food brings a man quickly into a conſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: ſo when the people of God through ſpirituall pride, ſhall grow careleſſe of vitall aſſiſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that they keepe not ſo cloſe to the word of life, nor to the Sacraments of life, nor to the great principle of life by an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and conſtant communion in prayer, no marvell if they grow dying perſons. It is with us in reſpect of God, as it is
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17566:18"/> with the plants in reſpect of the ſunne, which live or dye, flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh or decay upon their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction (if I may ſo ſpeake) and <note place="margin">Grace is not a life and ſtrength it ſelfe. Minuit ſupra vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti penuria, ſaid Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius, l. 1 de morb. cauſis.</note> neereneſſe with its heat.</p>
            <p>So our ſoules, yea and our graces live by that conjunction which they have with God; if we keepe not to him cloſe and neere, but draw off, what doe we but draw off from the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of our being and conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation?</p>
            <p n="4">4 Inconſiderate toleration of particular evils; not a timely expurgation of them.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> You know that if peccanthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours redound in the body, and be not conſidered of, and purged out in time, they may of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:17566:18"/> ordinary diſtempers, turne into deadly diſeaſes, and ſo it is with particular corruptions (admit they be ſuch as wee are pleaſed favourably to call infirmities) or any other ſinnes, if they be not quickly expelled and reformed, they may bring us neere the gates of death: one ſinne may bring on another, or the ſame ſinne may ſteale unto a ſtrange degree of ſtrength, ſo that a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon (unawares) is languiſhed extreamely, and whence comes this? not onely from an incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate admiſſion of ſinnes, but alſo from an untimely correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſinne.</p>
            <p>The ſoule ſhould preſently have phyſicked it ſelfe with,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:17566:19"/> firſt a right apprehenſion of the greatneſſe of the evill in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning: ſecondly, ſpeedy hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation before the Lord: thirdly, fervent ſupplication for mercy, and more ſtrength: fourthly, reſolute reformation and abandoning of it.</p>
            <p>But the neglect of theſe hath brought the ſoule into a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all languor, and perhaps into a deep conſumption of graces.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Defect of frequent exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations: though at our originall and firſt conviction of ſinne, and a ſinfull condition, we are very tender and circumſpect, and ever and anon feared, and overlooked our ſpirituall condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, whereby we found ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:17566:19"/> additions to our graces, yet after a while, after Chriſtians have got over the pangs of the firſt birth, and have procured more peace and comfort, (as if a gracious ſoul would thrive of it ſelfe) they are generally apt to keepe on the courſe of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but thinke it ſuperfluous, at leaſt not ſo neceſſary, often to ſearch, and view, and fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>now themſelves. And what now befals them? ſurely two great evils, <hi>viz.</hi> that the eſtate and operation, and acts of ſin, are not ſo ſtrictly eyed: ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the eſtate of their graces is not ſo well knowne and guarded againſt ſpeciall moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and temptations, whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:17566:20"/> it often fals out that the poor ſoul is reduced to great ſtreights and leanneſſe, the man cannot pray as heretofore, nor finde that love to God and Chriſt as heretofore, nor have that delight in the ordinances, nor doe that good in ſociety, nor receive that profit, nor feele that mournful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſpirit as heretofore: why? hee did let and ſuffer his ſpirituall eſtate to run on at ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards, and the leſſe ſearching of heart, the leſſe ſtrength of grace alwaies.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Defect of ſolemne humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations in extraordinary faſting and prayer. Thoſe meanes which beget our graces, are likewiſe ordained to preſerve
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:17566:20"/> them, and as the uſe of ſingular meanes confers more power and life to our graces, ſo a ceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the uſe of them, proves an exceeding decay unto them: it is as if you ſhould take away the pillars from the houſe, or the raine from the earth.</p>
            <p>Now this is certaine, that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary times of faſting and prayer, they have beene bleſt with power from heaven to make the ſtrongeſt temptation and corruption to flye, no ſinne is able to ſtand before them: and ſo likewiſe they have been bleſt with an anſwer of ſingular en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement &amp; addition to our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall eſtate: oh how cheerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, how tenderfully, how much
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:17566:21"/> more fully and fruitfully is thy ſoule inabled after thoſe du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties rightly performed? but Chriſtians grow very ſtrangers to theſe ſolemne duties, either totally omitting of them, or ſlubberlie performance of them, and therefore they get not that ſtrength over ſpirituall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, nor that fruitfull ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to their graces, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ſlip into dangerous lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhings and decayings.</p>
            <p n="7">7 Inactivity in our places and relations, is another cauſe of ſpirituall languiſhing and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caying. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> A lazy Chriſtian will quickly prove a dying Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an: the Phyſitians doe obſerve, that as too violent exerciſe over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throweth
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17566:21"/> health, ſo likewiſe too much reſt may cauſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame ſickneſſe, becauſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſuperfluous humours are not carried or breathed away, and the ſpirits and naturall heat are not ſtirred up to performe their proper functions.</p>
            <p>It is even ſo with Chriſtians, in reſpect of their graces; if they let them lye ſtill and dead, they will quickly grow weake and dying; though their life be an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted by an operation of Gods ſpirit, yet it is preſerved by an operation of our ſpirits; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore grace is compared to fire which muſt be ſtirred up and blowne: He who will not uſe grace, will quickly loſe it, or decay in it.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:17566:22"/>
            <p>But Chriſtians many times imploy not their graces, they do not any good with them, they doe not ſtir up their hearts to beleeve, to lay hold on God, to call upon him, to walke before him, they doe not lay their knowledge, their zeale, their love, &amp;c. in their particular rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; but live together, and do no good together, meet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and provoke not one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unto further holineſſe.</p>
            <p n="8">8 Laſtly, all perturbations or exceſſe in paſſions, cauſe a lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>V. Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel. l, 1. de morb, cauſis cap, 18, p.</hi> 198.</note> and therefore they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve in nature, that immoderate feare, or griefe, or anger, or joy, or agony (which conſiſts of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and feare) or deſire or care;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:17566:22"/> all theſe, or any of theſe by their immoderation, doe checke the ſpirit &amp; naturall heat, <hi>immarceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere ſpiritus &amp; calorem,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently diminiſh health and ſtrength. And ſurely ſo it is in the ſpirituall condition; all inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate affections are the empay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of grace, whether it bee deſires of the world, or delights in it, or fears of men, or griefe for loſſes, &amp;c. but I cannot now inlarge.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> I now come to the applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this point, which ſhall be in the firſt place, to reflect upon our owne hearts, to ſee in what condition our ſpirituall conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is; whether we be not Sardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, yea or not, either having a
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:17566:23"/> name onely, but are totally dead; or if we doe live, whether that life of ours be not growne ſo weake, that wee are almoſt dying.</p>
            <p>Reaſons to move you to ſearch your hearts in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, are theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Many among you (who <note place="margin">Three things.</note> profeſſe and have a name, and I hope, the truth alſo of grace) doe not get on, you doe not make progreſſe, you have not advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced your ſelves in your ſpirituall condition.</p>
            <p>Though the Lord hath given you plentifull and rich meanes, yet what you were many yeers agoe, the ſame you are now: a man may ſay of you, as we doe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:17566:23"/> of our friends, whom wee ſee perhaps once in ten yeeres, that they looke, and are juſt as wee found and left them then. So many of you, after many yeeres preaching and hearing, are juſt as you were, have not attained to any further perfection in holineſſe.</p>
            <p>Now it is an ill ſymptome, this; for a ſtaying heart is ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome otherwiſe then a decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heart. Creation, though perfect at once, yet it is not ſo with ſanctification; the old ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is, <hi>Non progredi eſt regredi,</hi> grace is either getting or loſing,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> like a river, either fuller or leſſer, or like an oake, growing or dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:17566:24"/>2 Many perſons expreſſe pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable decayings; all who know them, can ſee and ſay, how ſtrangely they are altered; they are ſcarcely knowne now to be Chriſtians, but by the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the moſt favourable charity, who formerly have beene very forward even to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplarity. The judgements of men are ſo altered with fond opinions, their ſtrictneſſe of converſation is ſo ſtrangely ſlack'd into that which they themſelves were wont to call a licentiouſneſſe of walking, there is ſuch a dumbneſſe growne in their families, and withall there is ſuch a chilneſſe come upon their affections; oh where is
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:17566:24"/> that thy former zeale, and love, and joy, and pitty, and broken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart, and flames for Chriſt, and deſires of ſtrength and aſſurance, and circumſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to pleaſe thy God?</p>
            <p n="3">3 Though we be not dead Chriſtians; yet if we be dying Chriſtians, it makes our condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion very evill, and very ſad.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Very evill, no man can <note place="margin">Evill. 1 Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally.</note> decay in good, but by ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that is bad; it is alwaies ſome ſinfull evill, which makes us to wither in ſpirituall good.</p>
            <p>And then it is a thing very <note place="margin">2 <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally,</hi>
               </note> evill in it ſelfe; if it be a ſinne not to thrive in grace, it muſt be a greater ſinne to be dying in grace.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:17566:25"/>
            <p>And then it occaſions much <note place="margin">3 <hi>Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually.</hi>
               </note> ſinne, for it were a wonder to ſee a man dying in grace, and not withall, living in ſinne; however, beleeve it, that ſinnes will live the more ſtrongly in thee, by how much the more weakely grace doth live in thee; when naturall heat growes low, then doe diſeaſes multiply and grow high, if that which ſhould keep downe ſinne, be kept downe by ſinning, how exceedingly ſinfull maieſt thou prove?</p>
            <p n="2">2 Very ſad: the Chriſtian condition is exceſſively perplex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and prejudiced by it, <hi>v. gr.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 There is an extenuation of <note place="margin">7 <hi>Effects of it.</hi>
               </note> our chiefeſt excellencies: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> our
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:17566:25"/> gold is now clipt and waſhed: Beloved, we have not more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all excellencies here on earth, then gracious and holy quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. If the naked ſoule be more worth then a whole world, what is grace, the which high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly elevates and advanceth the ſoule? But even our graces (in a decaying condition) are droop ing and pining: for a man to have a finger withering is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to that as to have his heart conſuming: to behold a candle put out, what is that, to behold the Sunne growing dim or purblind?</p>
            <p>When graces decay, then that <note place="margin">To loſe an houſe, a friend, &amp;c. but</note> which is as the heart to the members, or as the Sunne to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:17566:26"/> the earth, or as the ſoule to the body, a vitall ſpring, decayeth: as ſhe ſaid about the taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of the Arke, that we may ſay of diminution in grace. Now the glory is departing from <hi>Iſrael,</hi> now thy honour is lying in the duſt; the leſſe good thou groweſt, the more vile thou becommeſt, it is as if thy faire hand ſhould become le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prous, or thy ſunne ſet at noon day.</p>
            <p n="2">2 It is a depreſſion of our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly ſtrength; when <hi>Sampſons</hi> haire was off, he was then as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men; he loſt his haire, and loſt his ſtrength too.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> When the fountaines are low, and roots weake, then the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:17566:26"/> ſtreames prove thinne, and branches grow almoſt fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, for theſe are the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of being, and of aſſiſtance unto them.</p>
            <p>Our graces are a kinde of Springs to our gracious abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; when we be leſſe good, we ſhall alwaies doe the leſſe good, and the more evill. Thy wheels will move ſlowly, and thy feet (like thoſe of a ſicke man) will move ſtaggeringly and wearily; there will be much a doe to doe a little good: thy ſervices will be like the thinne rayes of gold, which can hardly be diſcerned for the multitude of aſhes and droſſe.</p>
            <p>Now this is a ſad thing,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:17566:27"/> when at the moſt, it is the moſt that a man can doe to beleeve, or to grieve for ſinne, or to love God and feare him, or to pray unto him, whereas heretofore he was able to beleeve and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, to mourne and lament, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3 A dampe upon our communions with GOD; there is a double commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
            <p>One is direct, which is our active communion with God, another is reflexive, which is Gods gracious communion with us: now by a dying in our ſpirituall conditions, there ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth a cloud and a dampe upon this reciprocall communion.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:17566:27"/>
            <p>Wee cannot ſo behave our ſelves to God, and God will not ſo behave himſelfe to us, as in former daies.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>
               </label> 1 For our communion with God, it will grow more ſtrange, leſſe confident, and more gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, ſmall for heart, leſſer for truſt, and leaſt of all for benefit and ſucceſſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2 For Gods communion with us, it will be eclipſed both in the effective and aſſiſting part of it, as alſo in the affective and comforting part of it: hee will not give thee his hand or his eye as formerly; <hi>David</hi> found (upon his great decay) not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a cloud in Gods face, but alſo a ſtrangeneſſe in Gods ſpirit, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.</note>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:17566:28"/> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 12. We doe by our no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious decaying, debarre our ſelves of much help from God, and of all manifeſting favour for the preſent.</p>
            <p>Deſertion is ever the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent of decaying.</p>
            <p n="4">4 A vexation and reſtleſneſſe in the conſcience; when we take our leave of grace, wee muſt take our leave of peace and comfort. A dead man (many times) reſts in peace, but a dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſtian is never without trouble; the remaining grace ſerves moſt to trouble us for our decayings in grace.</p>
            <p>Spirituall comfort uſually attends us, either upon great griefes for ſinne, or upon great
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:17566:28"/> progreſſes in duties. And ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall troubles uſually follow us, either upon great adventurings in ſin, or upon great remiſſions in holineſſe; for conſcience will trouble us as well for looſing what is good, as for commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting what is evill.</p>
            <p n="5">5 A great ſilence in heaven: the decaying Chriſtian ſhall either heare of much diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure from God, or little and no good from him.</p>
            <p>The ordinances (to which he now more perfunctorily ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies himſelfe) ſhall either bee dumb and ſpeake no incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or bitter, and ſpeake no ſtrength or peace.</p>
            <p>His prayers (which now are
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:17566:29"/> more cold and formall) ſhall either have no anſwer, or elſe the anſwer is more feare and trouble in ſpirit; God ſeemes to have no minde to ſpeake unto that man, who now hath ſcarce any minde to ſpeake unto his God.</p>
            <p n="6">6 A ſtrange ſuſpition of the reality of a ſpirituall condition; if grace be often put in diſpute when the Chriſtian cannot perceive it to thrive, how much more queſtionable will it be, when the ſame Chriſtian per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth it to abate and decay, (uſually it muſt be more then meere grace which muſt aſſure us of grace) foraſmuch as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing reſembles hypocriſie
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:17566:29"/> more then to be formall in our duties, and with it to be withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in our diſpoſitions.</p>
            <p>A dying Chriſtian looks very like to a dead hypocrite.</p>
            <p n="7">7 To all theſe may be added other evils, as horrid temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, externall miſeries, feares of death, &amp;c. but I may not inſiſt on every thing.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>But here it is demanded, how may we know whether wee be in a dying condition or not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I know no better way to diſcerne this, then by a juſt compariſon of things preſent with things paſt, as alſo by a faithfull obſervation of our owne ſpirits and graces: thus then,</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:17566:30"/>
            <p>1 Looke, firſt, upon your judgement and mindings, 2 up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your wils and affections, 3 upon your hearts and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, 4 upon your worſhip and ſervices, 5 upon your waies and converſations, ſo may you diſcerne whether you be dying or not.</p>
            <p n="1">1 For your judgements and mindes, formerly in theſe there were ſtrong endeavours to know the truths of God, and to ſearch out the myſteries of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and admirable appreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations of holineſſe and Gods favour, and ſweet meditations on the will of God; the minde was eminently taken up with God and Chriſt, and grace and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:17566:30"/> obedience and heaven.</p>
            <p>Is it ſo now? or rather doe not worldly things ſeeme great in our eyes, are not our mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings more for inferiour good, then for ſpirituall good? divine ſtudies, are they not rare, and poore, and tranſient glancings? where is that ſtudy to know God, or to ſee his favour in Chriſt unto thee? where is that reverend regard of the truths of God? where is that diligence to know the eſtate of thy ſoule? where is that ſweet delight thou tookeſt once to know Ieſus Chriſt as thine?</p>
            <p n="2">2 For your wils and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: time was, that thy will was a flexible will, eaſie to obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:17566:31"/> ſubmiſſive to the divine will, cheerefull in the duties of godlineſſe, much cloſing with divine promiſes, raviſhed with love to Chriſt, fearefull to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, carefull to pleaſe, deſirous of nothing more then Gods loving kindeneſſe, ſtrictly ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all evill, joyfull in this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, that God was thy portion; flouds of teares ſwelled thy griefe, heavenly delights ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thy ſoule, mercies were bleſt, threatnings feared, &amp;c. If in ſtead of theſe, thy will growes weary and ſurly, hard to be perſwaded, often clattering with the divine will, impatient of ſtrict obedience, indifferent to pleaſe, ſlow to hearken to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:17566:31"/> the counſels of God, and the mercies of God, and the threats of God are of ſmall efficacie; ſin is not ſo watched and loathed, God alone is not ſo delightfull and ſufficient, thy heart grows more inſenſible of ſinne, and hardly mournfull; thy delights are leſſe in heavenly things. Ah now, how is the mighty fallen, how is the noble plant degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated? &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3 For your hearts and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, compare them now with what formerly they were; how quicke was conſcience to direct, how apt was conſcience to checke, how tender was conſcience to offend? how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet was conſcience till peace
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:17566:32"/> was made, how exact was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to obey?</p>
            <p>Is it ſo now? thou canſt ſin; and conſcience ſtrikes not; God ſtrikes thee, but conſcience ſtrikes thee, not; conſcience ſtrikes thee, and thou careſt not; conſcience is growne ſleepy and drowſie, almoſt dead and ſcared; thou canſt omit duties, or performe them careleſly, ſlip and fall, and lie; and either conſcience ſaith nothing, or thou reformeſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
            <p n="4">4 And for thy worſhip and ſervice of God, how pretious were the ordinances unto thee, how delightfull? thou hadſt ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have ſpent a day with
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:17566:32"/> them, then a hundred daies in other employments: what ſecret impreſſions made the power of them upon thy heart, what griefes, what joyes, what degrees of perſwaſion, what expectations of hope, what fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance unto holy duties, what conflictings with, and conqueſts over ſinne and temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, what more ſerious care and diligence to walke with God.</p>
            <p>Oh why is it, whence is it, that now it is not as once it was? there is not that connatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralneſſe as formerly, the word works not on thee as formerly, the Sacrament works not on thee as formerly: the word of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:17566:33"/> threatning reveales wrath, and thou trembleſt not; the word of promiſe reveales goodneſſe, and thou loveſt it not; fidelity, and thou beleeveſt it not: the Sacrament opens the bloud of a Saviour, and thou thirſteſt not, thou rejoyceſt not; thou art growne dull under all, and bar ren after all; thy dead heart ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueth that thou art a dying ſoule.</p>
            <p n="5">5 The ſame may be ſaid for our converſation and wayes, if they be now dead in reſpect of ſinfulneſſe, or dead in reſpect of unprofitableneſſe, that wee are now become as the Heath that brings forth nothing, or as the Briar which brings forth
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:17566:33"/> thornes, that we turne all reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion into a diſcourſe or cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, or diſpute; we can eat and drink, and talke, and ſinne: how have the ſhadowes of death co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered us? how chill and langui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing are our graces turned?</p>
            <p>Well, ſeriouſly conſider of theſe things (you who heare me this day) and looke to it that you be not a dying people: more fearefull would your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition be, then the condition of others: for, firſt, you have more enlivening meanes then any people on the earth; no City like unto you for publike offers, or for private opportunities; yee are even exalted unto hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in the abundance and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:17566:34"/> choyce of ſpirituall helpes, and therefore your decayings would have more in the account then other mens; the more meanes of ſtrength and life (accidental<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) make dying diſeaſes to be the more deadly.</p>
            <p>2 Wee cannot but approve your flocking to the word and ſervice of God in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, as if you would take the kingdome of heaven by force; if now under ſo faire a complexion you ſhould be in a conſumption, that the vitals of godlineſſe ſhould ſlacke and pine away in your hearts and private walkings, this diſſonan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie would be not only ſhameful to your profeſſion, but alſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:17566:34"/> to your conſcience.</p>
            <p>2 Againe, another way per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons may diſcern whether they be dying and decaying.</p>
            <p>By an obſervation of the acts or operations of their graces; as if they be faint and more incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> you ſee that the root is leſſe able, when but a little fruit appeares on the tree, and that the Spring is fallen when the ſtreames ſcarce runne, which yet were wont to flow; when graces are ſcarce active, or are uneven in their generall actings, ſurely there is ſome ſpirituall languor in thee.</p>
            <p>O Chriſtian, thy faith doth not commit things to God as heretofore, and thy love is not
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:17566:35"/> ſo ſetled on Chriſt as heretofore, and thy patience cannot beare in any meaſure as heretofore, and thy ſorrow is dry, and thy zeale is cooled, &amp;c.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> If thy eye cannot ſee ſo well, but growes darker, and thy foot cannot goe ſo well, but growes lamer, and thy ſhoulders cannot beare ſo well, but grow weaker, it is an argument that naturall vigour is decaied. The ſame may be ſaid for our ſpirituall condition, if graces exert not themſelves in a former vigour, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>
               </label> I pray you to obſerve that graces are given unto us for three ends and uſes.</p>
            <p n="1">1 To be inclining principles to gracious or holy acts.</p>
            <p n="2">2 To be inlarging principles
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:17566:35"/> to pious performances.</p>
            <p n="3">3 To be cleanſing &amp; oppoſing principles of ſinful corruptions.</p>
            <p n="1">1 They are inclining prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples to gracious acts: the nature of man without grace, is like a dead man, who hath no diſpoſition to walke, but when grace comes into the ſoule, it doth enliven it, and ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble it, and incline or diſpoſe it unto holy operations, to minde, to will, to deſire, to doe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly works, as you ſee in Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> when converted, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing grace enclined him quite to another way, and to other acts, to pray, to preach Chriſt, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now where is that ancient diſpoſition in thee unto good
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:17566:36"/> duties? whence is that wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full unwilling eſſe and unto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardlineſſe of ſpirit in thee? how comes it to paſſe, that if thou doſt ſerve the Lord, it is as if it were of conſtraint, there is a kinde of averſeneſſe and hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing backe; thou doeſt not minde him in any meaſure, and his law is not in thy heart.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Againe, they are inlarging principles, they do not onely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able a man to good performan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for the matter, but alſo for the manner; they make us a willing people in the day of our offerings, and to delight to doe the will of God, and to be glad in going to the houſe of the Lord.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:17566:36"/>
            <p>But now there is not that rel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh of godlineſſe, there is not delightfulneſſe of ſervice, there is not that libertie and alacrity of ſpirit; thou art become a dull and heavy Chriſtian, as if there were not that ſuteableneſſe 'twi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t thy heart and holy duties, thou art growne very ſlothfull and careleſſe, and negligent in thy worke.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Laſtly, they are cleanſing and oppoſing principles of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, therefore compared to water which waſheth out the ſpots, and to fire which fetcheth off the ruſt; and as our corrupt fleſh is ſaid to luſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſpirit, ſo the renewed ſpirit is ſaid to luſt againſt the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:17566:37"/> fleſh, and they are contrary one to the other, ſtill in oppoſition and conflict.</p>
            <p>And ſo the time hath beene, that thou haſt found it, that grace did humble and cleanſe thy heart from the love of ſinne, and raiſed tender feare about it, and ſingular hatred and oppoſition of it; yea, the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thoughts of ſinne were an heavy burden to thee; how of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten (by reaſon of the rebellion in nature) haſt thou cryed out with Saint <hi>Paul, O wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliver me, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is it thus now, why is it not thus now? is ſinne quite ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or thinkeſt thou that grace
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:17566:37"/> and ſinne will ever be at truce? nay, but why doſt thou ſuffer thoſe contemplative evils to lodge in thy minde, or thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull imaginations to tickle and invegle thy affections? nay, how dareſt thou to be tamper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with acts, if not ſinfull, yet doubtfull, and as like ſins as can be, and which occaſion ſinne? yea, and ſins prevaile much on thee, as pride, vanitie, &amp;c. and under all this thy heart ſmites thee not, reſtraines thee not; the time hath beene, thou durſt not have beene or done this for a world, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>But if the caſe be ſo (may ſome tender conſcience reply) then I feare my eſtate is not right, for I never
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:17566:38"/> had ſo much adoe with a ſinfull na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture all my life, as of late, daies, and if the greater power of ſinne ſhewes the more weakened eſtate of grace, I am then the perſon in a dying condition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> To this I anſwer briefly. </p>
            <p n="1">1 You muſt diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the turbulency of ſinne, and the prevalency of ſinne; the ſpirituall condition is not decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, becauſe ſinne is more mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and rebelling, but becauſe ſinne is more prevailing and leading.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Betweene ſinne in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict, and ſinne in ſubjection; my grace is weakened when I yeeld to ſinne, but it ſtands in ſtrength when it ſtands in defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:17566:38"/> and conflict with ſinne: it argues the violence of ſinne to breake out againſt grace, and alſo it argues the potency of grace to keepe the ſoule from ſerving unruly and boyſterous luſts.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Betwixt ſinne in tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſinne in the affection, even a ſtrong caſtle may be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted, and a ſtout Chriſtian much tempted, then the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all part is weakened, when ſin is favoured: If as there is much temptation in thy ſinfull fleſh, ſo there is much deteſtation on thy ſpirituall part, thy bow yet abides in ſtrength.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>But another Chriſtian replies,</hi> if theſe ſignes of decaying be right,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:17566:39"/> 
               <hi>which you deliver, then ſurely I am in a dying frame; for heretofore when (as I thought) God looked on me in mercy, in quickening me from the dead, I had a very melting heart for ſinne, and a ſurpaſsing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y zealous love to God and his glory; but now I finde no ſuch height, and flames, and meaſures?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> To this I anſwer, </p>
            <p n="1">1 You muſt diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt equall ſenſibleneſſe, and equall ſpiritualneſſe; upon the inchoation of grace, there may be more ſenſibleneſſe, for as much as grace erects it ſelfe much in the affections (of whoſe acts we are more appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive, being more neere to ſenſe) but upon the advance in
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:17566:39"/> grace, there may be more ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualneſſe: though not ſuch a ſenſible griefe in the affection, yet a pure lothing of ſinne and diſplicence with our ſelves in the will.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Betwixt paſſionate expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and deliberate or judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous expreſſions; I confeſſe that heretofore thy zeale and love might be more paſſionate and violent, but now they worke upon more pure and mixt grounds, and for ever know, it argues the grace to be the more ſtrong, which can act its parts with leſſe turbulency and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietneſſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Betwixt grace generally diffuſed, and it particularly
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:17566:40"/> imployed: at the firſt all the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ranne as it were in one chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell; grace exerted it ſelfe moſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the humbling part, and therefore ſeemed to be very much, becauſe very much im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in a particular, but upon further knowledge of Chriſtian duties, grace diffuſeth its ſtrength to all the acts of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, it is not the leſſe, becauſe the more improved, onely it is the leſſe perceived; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> as health and ſtrength are when totally diffu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed over the whole body.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Betwixt interruption and corruption, ſpirituall principles may ſometimes be interrupted (<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> like a river which yet is ſcram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling over the bay) by tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions:
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:17566:40"/> the paſſages are not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ſo open for operation: the very ineptitude of a mans temper, may occaſion unequall expreſſions of the viſible act: <hi>actus Imperati:</hi> and yet there may be no weakening and decaying in the ſpirituall condition, for the inviſible frame, <hi>actus eliciti,</hi> are ſure and full ſtill; the will and deſires doe act as much as ever, though the tongue or hand cannot render it, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides this, the worke is made up by a ſecret humbling, which is ſo unavoydably hindred from an open acting.</p>
            <p n="6">6 But laſtly, if upon ſolid grounds, when wee are our ſelves, we finde a manifeſt ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:17566:41"/> of our preſent, with our former condition in grace; then counſell is better for thee then comfort, and mee thinkes no better adviſe can be preſcribed, then that of Chriſt himſelfe to the Epheſian Church, ſlaking in her firſt love, <hi>Remember from whence thou art fallen, and repent, and doe thy firſt works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>2</label> If though upon peruſall of theſe trials, you finde your ſelves not to be in a dying con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dition.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Then firſt bleſſe the arme of the Almighty God, who hath given grace, and upheld it.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Beſeech him for ever to preſerve and increaſe thy ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall qualities all thy daies; it is
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:17566:41"/> by his goodneſſe that thou art good, and of his ſtrength that yet thou abideſt in thy ſtrength.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Vſe all the meanes thou canſt to keepe up thy graces, that thou ſink not into a dying condition. Meanes to preſerve us from a dying condition be theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Be humble: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> the high tide quickly ebbes, and the higheſt ſunne is preſently declining: faith is the champion for our graces, and feare the watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and humility the nurſe. Spirituall pride fils our fancies, but impaires our graces: now a man thinkes he hath enough, and then he is ſure to loſe much; if any thing keepes us from
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:17566:42"/> being low in grace, it is this, that we ſtill grow low and poor in ſpirit. In the Rickets they have large heads, but weake feet, ſo, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Strive for further perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 17. 18.</note> in holineſſe, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 17. the moſt of what wee have, is but the leaſt of that we want: He that will not ſtrive to be better, will be worſe; in temporals we ſhould inſiſt more on our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits, and that will make us thankfull: in ſpirituals wee ſhould inſiſt more on our wants, and that will make us fruitfull, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 5. <hi>Adde to your faith, vertue, and to vertue know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> 6 v. <hi>and to knowledge tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, &amp;c.</hi> 8 v. <hi>for if thou doe
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:17566:42"/> theſe things, they make you that you ſhall neither be barren nor unfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 Quit all formality in all holy duties, take heed of the firſt coolings: much impiety may hang upon much indifferency: a coole ſpirit is alwaies a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſpirit: he who gives way to do duties in a ſlight manner, will after a while be able ſcarce to performe them in any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. But as the rule was <hi>Hoc age,</hi> ſo ſtill keep up thy ſpirit with the duty; ſtir up thy graces in all duties, put out thy heart and ſtrength in holy actions of praying and hearing, and that will keepe thee alive in grace.</p>
            <p>A conſcionable and cordiall
<pb facs="tcp:17566:43"/> acting of good is bleſſed, not onely with a preſervation of grace, but likewiſe with an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition and increaſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Maintaine an holy jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie and feare of decaying; <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is the man who feareth alwaies,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon, Prov.</hi> 28.</p>
            <p>Three things ariſe from this.</p>
            <p>One is tender watchfulneſſe againſt all decaying occaſions.</p>
            <p>Another is frequent ſearch and examination of our ſpirits and eſtates.</p>
            <p>Quicke repairings of all fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings: all which preſerve us from a notorious decaying or dying.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Be prudently ſerious in chriſtian ſociety; ſpend not thy
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:17566:43"/> houres in vaine diſputes, leſt while thou ſtudieſt odde noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, thou in the meane time lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt precious grace.</p>
            <p>There are diſputes which end onely in diviſion, and there are inquiries which tend to edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; rather ſtudie to make thy ſelfe better, then to prove ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be bad.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Keep up uprightneſſe, and by no meanes away with hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, ſay not the ſinne is little, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> for many a man hath dyed of a little wound, and we all know that the ſmall end of the wedge makes way for the greater; nor ſay, it is ſecret, a man may dye of a ſecret ſtab, as well as of an open wound:</p>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:17566:44"/>
            <p>When the children of the Prophets taſted of the pottage, they cried out <hi>Mors in olla,</hi> death is in the pot, and ſo ſhall wee finde upon experience, that there goes a dying influence with every ſinne.</p>
            <p>Therefore take heed of all ſinning, eſpecially of thoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt knowledge and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, theſe are <hi>peccata vulne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantia &amp; divaſtantia,</hi> wounding and waſting ſinnes. The tender heart and the upright, theſe are the living and the lively hearts.</p>
            <p n="7">7 I might adde, that we muſt apply our ſelves to a living Chriſt, and to living ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, &amp;c. but theſe alledged rules ſhall ſuffice for this time.</p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:17566:44"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> But ſuppoſe wee are in a dying condition, what meanes now?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> 1 Finde out the ſpeciall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes or cauſes of thy decaying, in what grace moſt, and by what meanes, and waies, and acts.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Be lowly humbled; that thou haſt ſo humbled and aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thy glory; Thou ſhouldeſt grieve exceedingly, that by thy great decayings, God hath been ſo much diſhonoured, his ſpirit grieved, religion ſhamed, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience wounded, and grace impaired.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Then uſe the meanes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed here in the Text, <hi>ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the things which remaine, that are ready to dye;</hi> whence wee
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:17566:45"/> come to the next propoſition, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> That ſpirituals, if languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and dying, are to be ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened. </p>
            <p>For the underſtanding of this aſſertion, premiſe with mee a few particulars,</p>
            <p n="1">1 That there is a difference betwixt the
<list>
                  <item>Implantation,</item>
                  <item>Perfecting,</item>
                  <item>Strengthening</item>
               </list> of holy princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</p>
            <p>The Implantation of them is nothing but their free and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall communication unto a perſon from Gods holy ſpirit; his hand alone ſets all theſe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly plants, and from his ſole goodneſſe and power are all
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:17566:45"/> thoſe ſtarres, thoſe ſhining and beautifull ſtars, created in our ſoules.</p>
            <p>Perfecting of holy princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, is nothing but a ſucceſſive addition unto grace received, a riſing or ſprouting of thoſe plants, a going on from a wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, to a ſtronger degree.</p>
            <p>The ſtrengthening of them differs from both, for it is not a new creation of holy princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, but a reſtauration of them, and ſo it differs from grace im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted, and though it be an addition to grace received, yet this addition is not to grace as meerely weake, but properly to grace as weakened, and ſo it differs from the perfecting
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:17566:46"/> of holy principles.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The ſtrengthening of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caying principles or habits of grace, it is a ſpirituall and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable reparation of them unto their former liberty, and ability, and efficacie.</p>
            <p>It is not a meere ſuſtaining of them in <hi>genere gratiarum,</hi> or in <hi>eſse vitali,</hi> that they ſhall not quite extinguiſh; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> as when a houſe is onely ſo kept, that it fals not to the ground, this is not ſufficient to ſuſtaining; for graces may be ſtrengthened as radicall habits, when yet they may be pining in their vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour, and remitted in their mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and graduals.</p>
            <p>But ſtrengthening of grace,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:17566:46"/> imports addition as well as ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtentation, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> like recovery which is health in ſome meaſure com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming and riſing againe.</p>
            <p>Nor is all regaining ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, unleſſe it be proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the eſtate of grace when it began to decay &amp; ſink: when the decayed Chriſtian recovers againe unto that ancient pitch of heavenly power and inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and unto his old liberty of holy acts, whether inward in the minde, will and affection, or outward in his open and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible duties; now hath he right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtrengthened himſelfe.</p>
            <p>It is true, that before he fully recovers that equall pitch, hee may be ſaid to ſtrengthen his
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:17566:47"/> graces by way of diſpoſition, but punctually by way of habit; the ſtrengthening implyes a new equality as it were to the latitude of his former conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p n="3">3 There is a threefold ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thening of decaying principles <note place="margin">A three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold ſtrength.</note> of holineſſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1 One is by way of authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and plaine cauſality; this ſtrengthening is the worke of the ſpirit of Chriſt Ieſus; for as he onely is life to a dead man, ſo he onely is medicine to a ſicke ſoule; his bloud is the onely comforting medicine to a trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled conſcience, and his ſpirit is the onely ſtrengthening me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine to a decayed Chriſtian.
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:17566:47"/> It is he who muſt ſet us upon our legs againe, and who muſt make our withered branches to flouriſh againe.</p>
            <p>Now Chriſt Ieſus doth <note place="margin">Chriſt ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens three waies.</note> ſtrengthen the languiſhed Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian (as I ſuppoſe) three waies.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Excitando,</hi> by awakening him out of his drowſie and deadly ſleepe, like thoſe to <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah, what meaneſt thou O ſleeper? ariſe;</hi> ſo doth Ieſus Chriſt awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the decaying Chriſtian, partly, <hi>per ſermonem ſonantem,</hi> by the powerfull knockings of the word, which will not let him reſt thus, but charge on him all the wrath of God, and the with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawments of his love, if hee will continue thus.</p>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:17566:48"/>
            <p>Partly, <hi>per ſermonem tonan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem,</hi> by ſome ſingular afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and neere corrections, ſcourging of him in ſome ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar outward mercies, that hee may ſee his ſpirituall loſſes in temporary ones.</p>
            <p>Partly, <hi>per ſermonem pulſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem,</hi> by his owne ſpirit, clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the eyes of his underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to open and reflect, and conſider on the decayed condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as alſo by exciting the conſcience bitterly, to accuſe and judge him for this recidua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and witherings, with much torment, feare, and ſhame.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Adjuvando,</hi> by conferring <note place="margin">Alvarez de aux. Gr. diſp. 88. p. 698.</note> on him actuall and efficacious ſtrength <hi>(ſpecialem concurſumro.
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:17566:48"/> bur actuale)</hi> whereby his will reſolves to forſake thoſe cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of death, and to turne backe againe into the pathes of lite, and is alſo inabled by that helping grace, both to bewaile its former decayings, and alſo earneſtly and conſtantly to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicate the throne of grace and mercy for pardon, and for ſtrength to recover.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Renovando,</hi> by a daily infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing (in the uſe of meanes) ſuch new meaſures and degrees of holineſſe, untill the decayed Chriſtian recovers his former ability and vigour, ſhaking off his corruptions, and attaining unto that ſtrength of holy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, faith, will, love;
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:17566:49"/> deſire, feare, care, obedience, as heretofore.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Another, is by way of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery and office: this concerns the Paſtors of flockes, who ſhould conſider the eſtate of their ſheepe, and if they finde any to wander, to reduce them into the way of truth; if any to be weake, to beare them up in their armes with comfort, if any to be pining and decaying, to ſtirre them up by holy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofes and pious counſels and directions for all the waies of a ſpeedy and ſafe recovery; and many interpreters thinke this the principall ſtrengthening meant and intended in this place.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:17566:49"/>3 A third by way of perſonal duty, and ſo the decaying Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſtrengthens himſelf, when being awakened, and excited, and aſſiſted by the Spirit of Chriſt, he applies himſelfe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and continueth in the uſe of all holy and raiſing meanes, whether private or publicke, or both, untill God againe ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens what he hath wrought in him.</p>
            <p>This ſtrengthening is partly</p>
            <p>Privative in the expulſion of thoſe diſeaſes and occaſions which have impaired the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall condition.</p>
            <p>Poſitive, in a continuall ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couring of the ſpirituall conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, till it recovers to its ancient
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:17566:50"/> degree and ſtation.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>But why muſt the ſpirituall condition be thus ſtrengthened?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reaſons hereof are many.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> 1 Spirituall decaies are excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding loſſes, therefore to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired and ſtrengthened: they are a loſſe</p>
            <p>In that which is our excellency; holineſſe is the glory of a God, and the dignity of a Chriſtian; it is holineſſe which makes thee to differ from men, more then reaſon makes thee to differ from beaſts: If with him in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell thou ſhouldeſt loſe thy ſheep, or with her in the Goſpel, thou ſhouldeſt loſe thy groat, thou wouldeſt ſeeke to recover them: how much more when
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:17566:50"/> thy crowne is loſing? &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In that which is our ſafety: graces are not onely <hi>ornamenta,</hi> beautifull garments, but <hi>muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta,</hi> powerfull weapons: thou loſeſt thy weapons in the very field before thine enemies: if thou loſeſt thy ſpirituals, and makeſt thy ſelfe naked, ſo that any temptation may inſult over thee and wound thee: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> at leaſt thou canſt not ſo well wield and uſe thy weapons: a broken arme what can it doe, eſpecially with a dull weapon, againſt ſtrong and skilfull adverſaries?</p>
            <p>In that which is our ſerenity: the weakened grace, and the wounded conſcience ſtill goe together: or if not, then it is the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:17566:51"/> dying grace, and the dead con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which is farre worſe then the other.</p>
            <p>In that which is our felicity: ah unhappy Chriſtian, who when thy bow abode in ſtrength, couldeſt ſee a loving God, enjoy a gracious Father, couldeſt ſpeake to him much, and heare from him much; but now haſt changed thy confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence into feares, thy ſunne into darkeneſſe, thy communion into ſtrangeneſſe, thy glory into ſhame.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Who knowes what the end will be, if thou ſtrengthen not thy decaying graces? The Lord knowes how farre thou maieſt fall, if thou wilt not
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:17566:51"/> thinke of riſing.</p>
            <p>Thou ſeeſt how poore a crop of duties comes from thy decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing graces: thou feeleſt thy affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions almoſt gone: thou ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeſt not only a weakneſſe, but a wearineſſe in holy ſervices: thou findeſt thy appetite gone from the word, thou knoweſt thy neglect of many a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: thou canſt not but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a vanity to ariſe in thy minde, in ſtead of heavenly pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and a more delightfull conſociation with vaine and idle perſons, then with ſolid and fruitfull Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Yea and ſince thy graces have beene weakened, eaſie tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions have beene very likely (if
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:17566:52"/> not altogether) effectuall to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnare thee to great tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: from many omiſſions thou art now ready for great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> ſo that like a ſtone running downe a hill, or a man carried further and further into the ſea, thou doeſt indanger (what in thee lies) the very ſoule and ſalvation of thy ſelfe; and the love of God is it not ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting? are not his frowns riſing?</p>
            <p>And here will be work now made for that miſerable ſoule of thine, which hath ſo farre gone from home, and is depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from thy fathers houſe?</p>
            <p n="3">3 We are bound to keep our graces in repaire, and more then ſo, <hi>orgo,</hi> we are not to reſt in a
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:17566:52"/> decaying eſtate, but to recover, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> As the Tenant who takes an houſe is bound to keepe it in repaire, that it may be habitable againſt winde and weather, ſo muſt we keepe up the graces given unto us, and not let them ſinke at all.</p>
            <p>Nay more then ſo, wee are bound againſt not onely decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, but againſt meere ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: wee muſt proceed from faith to faith, we muſt perfect holineſſe in the feare of God, we muſt grow in the love and knowledge of our Lord Ieſus, we muſt abound in all the fruits of righteouſneſſe, we muſt uſe and increaſe our talents, it will
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:17566:53"/> not be an anſwer of proofe, to retaine our naked talent, and ſay, Maſter, there is thine own.</p>
            <p>The firſt uſe of this point ſhall bee to ſtirre us up to the <note place="margin">Vſe.</note> practiſe of this duty. I will not ſpend time to demonſtrate that we need ſtrengthening. I may ſpeake my conſcience with grief, that generally we are a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caying people, in the powers of godlineſſe, and flames of holy affections, yea our own conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences ſecretly teſtifie againſt us this day, that ſo it is; yea, the judgements of God, the fire of his wrath which begins to burn and flye abroad in this City yet againe, teſtifies as much: and therefore my exhortation to us
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:17566:53"/> all, is, that we wiſely conſider of our dyings and decayings: ah! if the Plague ſhould breake into our dwellings, and take us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in our decayed eſtates, a tormenting ſore, and a tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting conſcience, a dying ſpirit, and a dying body, both at once, the Lord knowes the woful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſuch a condition. There are onely three things which I ſhall commend unto you for the application of this, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1 The motives to excite us.</item>
               <item>2 The meanes to perform it. <note place="margin">Three things.</note>
               </item>
               <item>3 The manner of doing it.</item>
            </list>
            <p>1 The motives,</p>
            <p>To excite us to ſtrengthen our ſpirituall condition, ſhall <note place="margin">Seven diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages.</note> be drawne from the diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages in a weakned, &amp; the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:17566:54"/> of a ſtrengthened conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p n="1">1 In reſpect of duties, the Chriſtian is to be Gods workman; he is the ſervant of the Lord, who impoſeth on him not a few, but many workes, not eaſie, but (many times) difficult workers, not for a while, but conſtant workes, ſuch duties, that a little know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge wil not ſerve the turn, nor a little wiſdom, nor a little faith, nor a little patience, &amp;c. ſome of theſe duties are active, ſome paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, ſome reſpecting his general, ſome his particular calling, ſome of relation to God, ſome to man, ſome to himſelfe. Now the weakened Chriſtian, hee is no body to the ſtrengthened
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:17566:54"/> Chriſtian for duties, for every man is, as his ſtrength is, and our actions (for the courſe of them) are as the ability of the ſoule is from whence they come.</p>
            <p>The weakened Chriſtian comes very ſhort of the other, both for</p>
            <p>His adaptation of ſpirit unto duty, there is not that connatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralneſſe (if I may ſo ſpeake) of his ſpirit to ſpirituall offices; du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties come hardly from him,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> like a ruſty key to open a doore; hee doth his worke with a more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſed ſpirit, not freely, but like a ſickeman, he goes very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and is quickly weary, and poorely, not fully, whereas the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:17566:55"/> ſtrengthened, Chriſtians duties flow from him as from an eaſie principle, and lively and quicke cauſe.</p>
            <p>His adequation of duty to the rule; He doth not minde the rule of holy actions ſo much, nor doth hee proportion his workes to the commands, God may command much more then he doth, for ordinarily the decayed Chriſtian is guilty of many omiſſions.</p>
            <p>Hee failes wonderfully oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in paſſing over the duty of prayer, or reading, or hearing, &amp;c. But the ſtrengthened Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, he is for all duties, difficult as well as eaſie, private as well as publique, though hee cannot
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:17566:55"/> intenſively anſwer the rule for duty, yet extenſively hee doth; knowingly and willingly hee omits no duty.</p>
            <p>His affective cooperation with duty: hee doth duty, but without ſuch co-working affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, more formally; he doth pray and heare perhaps, but it is coldly and ſleepily, it is not as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> but as if it were ſome indifferent worke, he acts with a careleſſe and indifferent ſpirit. His eye is not ſo full on Gods glory, nor is his heart ſo warme in prayer, &amp;c. His coles of fire burne in a cold hearth: He is not lively in living works, but performeth ſpirituall works without much ſpiritualneſſe.</p>
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:17566:56"/>
            <p>But the ſtrengthened Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian hath workings in his workes, or as in <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> there was a wheele within a wheele; he ſerves the Lord with a fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent ſpirit, and with all his ſoul; hee is exceeding glad to obey, and is much grieved that he can obey the Lord no better.</p>
            <p>Acceptation of duty: the Lord doth not looke ſo upon his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, as on the duties of a ſtrengthened Chriſtian: it is true, that the Lord doth not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe the day of ſmall things, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven weake ſervices are graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly reſpected by him, but when Chriſtians weaken their owne operations, they doe weaken alſo Gods acceptations,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:17566:56"/> for the Lord is pleaſed different<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to anſwer his ſervants accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their different diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and tempers; faint ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers have but faint anſwers, and reſolute petitioners get plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full anſwers from him of good.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In reſpect of the ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, here alſo the weakened Chriſtian is very ſhort of the ſtrengthened Chriſtian, both</p>
            <p>For preparation unto them, his heart is not put in ſuch a frame to come and converſe with God, he will not take that paines before he comes to the word, hee doth not by prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent meditations and prayers, bring ſuch a receptivity and and teachableneſſe of heart to
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:17566:57"/> the word; nor for the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: perhaps he comes and thruſts on the worke, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tires not himſelfe, examines not himſelfe, humbles not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, hungers not, thirſts not, nor conſiders his particular neceſſities, ſo rightly to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe his ſoule for an holy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God, but is more full of carnall indulgence to himſelfe, and ſtudy rather for apologies to excuſe his neglect, then by preparative duties to fit himſelfe:</p>
            <p>For application of them, hee ſtands under the ordinances with more diſtractions, with leſſe attentions, with an unclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſpirit; the word workes
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:17566:57"/> not ſo on his heart, nor his heart on the word. He ſtands under the ordinances with a more diſtracting ſpirit, or elſe with a more fearing ſpirit, leſt the Lord will finde him out for his revoltings, and either hee dares not come to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or if he doth, hee is not able for his life almoſt to be confident and perſwaded of Gods love towards him in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>For fructification, he buyes not at the market, ſuckes not, and thrives not by the breaſts, nor makes that uſe of them as the other doth; nor doth hee improve them ſo to the benefit of his ſpirituall condition, as
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:17566:58"/> the other doth, the counſels, commands, exhortations, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofes, promiſes, they are generally to him in his weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned eſtate, as water on the rock, or as the waves to <hi>Ionah</hi> ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the ſhip, they have not that <hi>virtutem moventem,</hi> that authority over his drowſie ſpirit.</p>
            <p>But the ſtrengthened Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian hath farre more eaſie paſſages, the word and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment have their ſweet and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile impreſſions, on his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, will, and affections: by diſcoveries of ſinne, and threatnings, he feares the Lord; and hates ſinne more. By diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries of goodneſſe and mercy,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:17566:58"/> and Chriſt, his faith gets more, and his love riſeth more. By diſcoveries of duties, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, his cares and deſires abound more in him; they are ſtill humbling, or ſtill purging, ſtill raiſing, or ſtill upholding of him, he is more and more built up and edified in his holy faith, his communions with God are more cordiall, and more beneficiall: there is ſtill a fuller and ſweeter conjunction betwixt his ſoule and Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3 In reſpect of corruptions, which are the very bane and poyſon, and ſhame of his ſoule, and ſore woundings and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairings; the weakened Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian is found much underfoot,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:17566:59"/> and is more in bondage, and leſſe ſenſible of it: gray haires appeare more on him, unruly luſts get more head againe, and he either hardly feeles them, or faintly reſiſts them: He is now become as a wounded man, over whom every coward can inſult.</p>
            <p>The ſtrength of tender per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of ſinne failes, and the ſtrength of reſolute oppoſition, and the ſtrength of frequent conqueſt, ſo that his ſoule is much imbaſed by luſts, his reſiſtance are either,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 None.</item>
               <item>2 Or faint.</item>
               <item>3 Or fruitleſſe.</item>
            </list>
            <p>But he is overborne by the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:17566:59"/> tide, more eaſily, like an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfull rower, or a ſicke man by a thruſt.</p>
            <p>But it is otherwiſe with the ſtrengthened Chriſtian, who now can leade captivity cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive: he is mighty in prayer, and reſolute in defiances, and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally happy either in making ſinfull motions to flye, or in preſerving his ſoule from yeeld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto them; either hee is more quiet, or leſſe guilty: He is a greater enemy to ſinne, a ſurer conquerour, and ſtill a leſſer ſervant.</p>
            <p n="4">4 In reſpect of converſation, it is true that the Chriſtian muſt be gold without, and gold within; hee muſt be like the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:17566:60"/> heavens, excellent in ſubſtance, and beautifull in appearance; a good heart is not enough, but alſo a good life and walking, like a Spring which is for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good, and not for private. But the weakened Chriſtian in his converſation, fals ſhort of the others, who is ſtrengthened in many reſpects, <hi>v. g.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 For ſtrictneſſe, though it be a kinde of garment, yet it hangs more looſely, and like one of the Planets; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> though a ſtarre in heaven, yet ſometimes nearer, ſometimes more diſtant from the equinoctiall. There is not that exact conſcionable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in holy walkings, but a ſordid complying many times
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:17566:60"/> with the acts and waies of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy ſocieties, or at leaſt his graces are out-dared, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awed, ſo that when hee ſhould expreſſe them for Gods glory, he is afraid to ſpeake or worke,</p>
            <p n="2">2 For profitableneſſe: every good man ſhould be like a tree, on which, one may gather fruit; he is to be a ſteward of the manifold gifts, not inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, but imploying of them for the benefit of others: his boxe of oyntment ſhould be opened: If thou be good, thou art bound alſo to doe good, for graces are given not onely to make us good, but alſo to make us to doe good; but thus it is not with the decaying Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:17566:61"/> He being now fallen into a penurious ſtocke of grace, hath almoſt loſt the art and skill of profitableneſſe, his acts ſeeme rather to be thoſe of civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, then piety, he may be as facetious, but is not ſo religious in converſings; his diſcourſes are more cenſorious and inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, then ſubſtantiall and edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: I confeſſe that ſome Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians cannot ſo draw out their treaſure, through a baſhfulneſſe of ſpirit, but he is growne leſſe active, becauſe leſſe able; his barrenneſſe is in the cauſe, and not in the inſtrument.</p>
            <p>So that he may eat and drink with others, but no good comes from him; his lips pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:17566:61"/> not knowledge, nor doth his communication adminiſter grace to the heare: whence it followes, 1 That God hath lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or no glory by him: 2 That the Saints have little or no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in him: 3 That his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience hath little or no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in it ſelfe.</p>
            <p n="3">3 For cleerneſſe, his river is not ſo ſweet, but ever and anon it proves brackiſh; his ſunne, though it runs its courſe, yet it is frequently clowded, ſo is it with his life, he is not doing of good ſo, but withall ever and anon, he is doing of ſome evill: his weakened graces cannot beare him up againſt ſtrong oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions and temptations: his
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:17566:62"/> gold lies much in the aſhes, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> and like a lame man, he is not only halting in his beſt motion, but ever and anone quite downe, the ſnuffe gets above his candle.</p>
            <p n="4">4 For delightfulneſſe, hee is almoſt a ſtranger to exact Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and doth not honour them ſo much as formerly, but ſecretly feares their company, and judgement; he is perhaps more aſhamed, or elſe more afraid of them: his conſcience is yet ſo apprehenſive, that hee interprets every glance as a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret checke of his decayings. Thus is it not with the ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened Chriſtian, whoſe graces are high, carefulneſſe great, uſefulneſſe large, godlineſſe
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:17566:62"/> even, and* great delights taken <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pſal.</hi> 16. 1.</note> up amongſt the beſt and choi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſt Chriſtians. Hee himſelfe ſtill growes better, and others by him.</p>
            <p n="5">5 In reſpect of conſolation: the declining ſunne creates the longer and darker ſhadowes, and the decaying Chriſtian brings on himſelfe either the ſharper terrors, or deeper griefs, the ſicke bed is full of paines; neither his owne ſpirit, nor Gods Spirit ſpeake peace unto him. He who of bad begins to be good, may have much tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility; but he who of good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes leſſe good, ever becomes more undelightfull to God, and moſt unquiet with himſelfe.</p>
            <pb n="110" facs="tcp:17566:63"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> The ſhip which goes out in low ebbes, fals fouleſt on the ſands, ſo Chriſtians who ebbe in graces, ſhall alwaies flow with ſorrowes.</p>
            <p>But it is otherwiſe with the ſtrengthened Chriſtian, for riſing graces breed ſtronger comforts and longer; there is not onely no troubling accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but a moſt ſurpaſſing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation in conſcience; he hath a better heart, and ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore finde a more quiet ſpirit, for conſcience ſpeakes peace anſwerable to our being more good, and doing of it. Alas, that thou ſhouldeſt ſtill walke like a <hi>Benoni,</hi> a childe of ſorrow, whereas the other Chriſtian
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:17566:63"/> lives like a <hi>Barnabas,</hi> a ſonne of conſolation.</p>
            <p n="6">6 In reſpect of affliction: the weakened in active graces, is ever moſt weake in paſſive duties: generally hee hath more croſſes, and (or himſelfe) leſſe wiſedome and ſtrength to bear them; becauſe hee is growne worſe, therefore his afflictions are increaſed, and becauſe his abilities are ſunke, therefore the afflictions cruſh and prick him much the more.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sampſon</hi> who could eaſily breake thorow many cords, and barres, yet when weaken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, a few Philiſtines were too hard for him.</p>
            <p>He cannot be ſo patient, nor
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:17566:64"/> yet ſo confident, nor yet ſo dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in a ſuffering condition.</p>
            <p>His weakened graces can neither adminiſter ſtrength, nor yet ſubdue thoſe workings of impatience, ſo that he is almoſt ſunke and ſplit with calamities, his decayed ſhip can ſcarſe abide any foule weather.</p>
            <p>But when perſonall ſickneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes come, and the apprehenſion of death (at which times his conſcience is thoroughly wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened) ah how bitter, how ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible are the thoughts and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes of his heart at ſuch a time, much like thoſe of him who apprehends his condition not to be good.</p>
            <p>Oh how the pulſes of his
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:17566:64"/> diſturbing and diſturbed conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence worke? what reflexions on his former waies? what compariſon of his former flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhings, with preſent decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings? what feares of approch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before the Lord? what ſmart ſentences on himſelfe, what ſudden and vehement exclamations? Oh Lord! (ſaith he) I would not yet dye, I am fallen much from my God: Lord, ſpare me a little, that I may recover my ſtrength (my decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſtrength) before I go hence, and ſhall be no more ſeene.</p>
            <p>It is not ſo with the ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened Chriſtian, but as in active duties, hee is more for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, ſo in paſſive duties he is
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:17566:65"/> more ſufficient; in loſſes, in croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, yea in death it ſelfe hee is more ſubmiſſive and confident; he can (with <hi>Iob)</hi> be as willing to receive evill at the hand of God as good, and doth not only rejoyce in his favours, but in his ſtrokes, and is as ready to go to his father, as to ſerve God his good maſter.</p>
            <p n="7">7 In reſpect of Gods mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation; the Lord is pleaſed diverſly to manifeſt himſelfe to his people, ſometimes in admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable motions and ſuggeſtions of his ſpirit, ſometimes in more quick excitations of their ſpirits, ſometimes in ſingular confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of them with aſſiſtances for extraordinary works; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:17566:65"/> by ſecret impreſſions of his favour and love upon their conſciences, which doth revive their hearts as wine, and ſatisfie their ſoules as with marrow, ſo <hi>David</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63. But now the weakened Chriſtian, he darkens this heaven over his head, he hath not that comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſight of God, that aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of his favour, that joy of the holy Ghoſt; <hi>David</hi> loſt the joy of the ſpirit, and the voyce of gladneſſe; the arme of God is <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.</note> not ſo revealed in him for doing of good, nor the face of God ſo open unto him at all.</p>
            <p>Whereas the ſtrengthened Chriſtian findes it otherwiſe, he hath a better heart, and a
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:17566:66"/> fairer day; his communion is ſweet with the Lord; hee ſtill ſeeks the Lord, and often findes him, enjoyes him in his power, and enjoyes him in his gratiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; the Lord meets him that worketh righteouſneſſe, and remembers him who remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers the Lord in their waies.</p>
            <p>Now thinke on theſe things (O thou fallen and decayed Chriſtian) and reſt not in thy weakeneſſe, but recover and ſtrengthen thy ſpirituals againe.</p>
            <p>Three things I will let fall, <note place="margin">Three things.</note> which perhaps may fetch and quicken thee againe.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Though thou art far ſunk, yet thou maieſt be raiſed again.</p>
            <p n="2">2 If thou doeſt riſe again, the
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:17566:66"/> Lord will graciouſly pardon thy decaies.</p>
            <p n="3">3 If thou wilt ſet upon the ſtrengthening worke, the Lord will worke in thee ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſtrength.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Thou maieſt be raiſed and ſtrengthened againe, and that may appeare thus unto thee.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Repentance is poſſible for any ſinnes which are commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and if renewed repentance be poſſible, then a recovery a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine is poſſible, for as much as our recovery again conſiſts very much in a renewed repentance.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Yea and we have examples of weakened Chriſtians, ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened againe, as we know in <hi>David,</hi> exceedingly wounded,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:17566:67"/> but yet recovered, and <hi>Peter</hi> grievouſly falling, but graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly riſing againe.</p>
            <p n="2">2 If thou doeſt ſtrengthen thy condition, the Lord will merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully pardon thy former decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: I confeſſe that there may be ſore grounds of feare to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangle and depreſſe the ſpirit of a decaid Chriſtian, for his ſins (by which he hath decayed) may perhaps be hainous for the kinde, and alſo high for the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, being againſt knowledge, againſt the workings of conſcience, againſt the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of his graces, againſt the tender love of God in Chriſt, ſhewed to him more then to another, ſo that his heart may ſtrongly miſgive him, whether
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:17566:67"/> the Lord will ever looke upon him more, and accept of him into favour. But this I ſay, that be thy decayings what they will, either for the matter of them, or cauſes of them, or cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of them; if thou doeſt riſe againe by a renewed repentance, I aſſure thee that the Lord will pardon thee, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of thee in Chriſt; looke, as the Lord pardons all the ſinnes of thy unconverted condition upon thy initiall repentance, ſo he will pardon all the ſinnes of thy converted condition, upon renewed repentance, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee cals upon backſliding and declining people to returne unto him, and promiſeth both
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:17566:68"/> to heale them, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14. 4. and to <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14. 4.</note> love them freely <hi>(ibid.)</hi> which is as much as to pardon them, but ſee the pardon expreſly, <hi>Micah.</hi> 7. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mic.</hi> 7. 18.</note> 18. <hi>Who is a God like unto thee, that pardoneth iniquity, and paſseth by the tranſgreſsion of the remnant of his beritage, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 If thou wilt ſet upon the ſtrengthening work, the Lord will worke in thee ſufficient ſtrength for the worke. There is a difference betwixt a man in his converſion, there indeed he is without all ſtrength, hee can doe nothing; and the Chriſtian in his reſtauration, there is now ſome living ability in him, which can yet doe a little, act a little, ſtrive a little, at leaſt in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailings
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:17566:68"/> and deſires. Now if thou doeſt in any ſincere degree ſet upon the right and full meanes of thy recovery, the Lord God will come in with his owne ſtrength. Hee will ſtrengthen what hee hath wrought in thee, and will work the will and the deed in thee, his own works in thee.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>But then you will reply, what meanes may a decayed Chriſtian uſe to recover and ſtrengthen himſelfe againe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> I conjecture that the beſt courſe is this.</p>
            <p n="1">1 A ſerious conſideration of <note place="margin">Seaven Meanes.</note> their condition; this is the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell which Chriſt gave to the Church of <hi>Epheſus</hi> (decaying in
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:17566:69"/> her firſt love) <hi>Remember from</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Revel.</hi> 2</note> 
               <hi>whence thou art fallen;</hi> ſeriouſly conſider, take to heart, peruſe and judge over thy eſtate, what it was formerly, what it is now; what ſtrength then, what weaknes now, how much glory God had then, what diſhonour God hath now; what good thou diddeſt then, what evill thou doeſt now; what peace in conſcience then, what wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in conſcience now; what eſtimation among the Saints then, what ſtrengthening of the hands, and opening of the mouthes of the wicked now?</p>
            <p>And this is an excellent meanes to worke upon thy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, or rather to worke of thy
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:17566:69"/> ſpirit; <hi>David</hi> conſidered his wayes, and turned his feet to Gods teſtimonies.</p>
            <p n="2">2 A deep humiliation which will follow upon this; thou muſt breake through all buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and pleaſures, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediments, and retire thy ſelfe in a more ſolemne manner, (more then once or twice) and ſet thy ſelfe before the Lord, and fall down before his footſtoole with ſhame and confuſion of face, with bitter weepings and lamentations, with ſound judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and condemnations of thy ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Ah, how thou ſhouldeſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitely afflict thy ſoule, that thou ſhouldeſt be ſo mad and
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:17566:70"/> vile to loſe a God, to loſe any thing of the graces of a God, for a ſinnes ſake, or a worlds ſake.</p>
            <p>That the Lord ſhould ſhew thee more love then another, and intruſt thee with grace (the leaſt dram where of is more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious then all the world) and yet thou ſhouldeſt decline from the Lord, not anſwer this truſt, not uſe thoſe talents which have yeelded ſo much profit and comfort, being improved, but decay in them, and fall behinde hand, yea even under mighty meanes of ſtrength alwaies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued unto thee; and theſe things ſhould cut and grieve, and afflict, and humble thy ſoul exceedingly.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:17566:70"/>3 A ſolid reſolution: thou muſt with full purpoſe of heart reſolve not to reſt in thy decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed condition, but to ſhake off all the cauſes and occaſions of thy decayings.</p>
            <p>If any wickedneſſe hath got into thy heart, thou muſt put it farre away from thy taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and if the morſels have beene ſweet, thou muſt caſt them out with godly ſorrow as bitter as gall and wormwood.</p>
            <p>If careleſneſſe and ſlothful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſpirit hath cauſed thy decayings, thou muſt (with the Church in the <hi>Canticles)</hi> ſtand no longer upon, how ſhall I riſe and put on my coat? but riſe thou muſt, and get out of thy
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:17566:71"/> ſlothfull bed, and thruſt from thee a neglecting and negligent diſpoſition.</p>
            <p>Or if the world hath cauſed thy decayings, either in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of it and gaine, or in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of it and reſpects, or in the friendſhip of it and acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, thou muſt reſolve to bid them all farewell. Think on it O Chriſtian, what gets he for profit, who loſeth in his graces, or for honour, who abaſeth himſelfe in his graces, or for love, who loſeth himſelfe in the favour of his God? Ah poore ſoule, thou mayeſt curſe the day that ever thou kneweſt what did belong to thy drudgings in the world, and unto thy great
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:17566:71"/> friends in the world, and thy ſociety with ſuch and ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: at firſt thou didſt converſe with them with a regretting ſpirit, then with a ſilent ſpirit, then with an yeelding ſpirit; many, many a day haſt thou come home with conſcience accuſing and ſmiting of thee, unto which hadſt thou heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, thou hadſt been much pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved: well, well, if ever thou wouldeſt recover thy ſpirituall ſtrength, thou muſt perempto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily reſolve on it to ſever from wicked ſociety, better farre to be a poore man, and a rich Chriſtian, then to thrive any way, and bee decaying in grace.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:17566:72"/>4 An active reformation: <hi>Remember (ſaid Chriſt) from whence thou art fallen, and doe thy firſt workes:</hi> ſo ſay I now, goe to thy old workes againe, be tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for thy ſoule, ſet up prayer againe, and reading againe, and hearing againe, and holy medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and conference againe, and ſolemne humiliations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, ſtir up thoſe coales and cinders of grace; there is life yet in thee, oh act thy life, faith can doe ſomething for thee, though it cannot ſee comfort for thee, yet it can ſee helpe and ſtrength for thee; godly ſorrow can mourna little, ſet it to work, perhaps it may quickly riſe to a floud upon particular ſurveyes, and ſo ſet repentance on work,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:17566:72"/> yea, and all thy ſoul, thy minde, thy judgement, thy memory, thy affections to worke in all the duties of thy generall and particular condition.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Ardent ſupplication, for it is the Lord who muſt ſhew this power in thy weakeneſſe, <hi>Pſal. 86. O turn unto me and have</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 86. 16.</note> 
               <hi>mercy upon me, give thy ſtrength unto thy ſervant:</hi> Beſeech him to pitty thee, beſeech him to ſuccour and helpe thee, to be thy ſtrength and thy ſalvation; to beat downe and weaken the ſinnes which have ſo much weakened thee, to crucifie thy heart to the world, which hath ſo much crucified thy heart unto thy God. To breath upon
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:17566:73"/> thy graces as hee did upon the dry bones, to ſtirre up and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive them by his Almighty ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, to put his hand of power, upon thy hand of weakeneſſe, as the Prophet did upon the Kings, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Yea, and never give him o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver till then, that though thou haſt beene a backſliding childe, yet hee is a gracious Father; though thou haſt been unfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, yet hee is faithfull; though thou art weakened, yet he is the everlaſting God, the Creator of the ends of the earth, who fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not, who can give power to the faint, and to them that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 40. 28.</note> have no might, he can increaſe ſtrength.</p>
            <pb n="131" facs="tcp:17566:73"/>
            <p>Yea, and that yet there is ſomething of his owne in thee, though very little, yet ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and that holineſſe which he did once implant by a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hand, he is now as able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive and ſtrengthen it by his Almighty power.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Carefull application: now goe to the healing and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thening waters; thou haſt knowne the waies of God, and his goings in the Sanctuary, how he hath wrought won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders for the dead, many a Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple hath got ſtrength there, and many a diſconſolate ſoule hath found comfort there, in his word and in his Sacrament, there hath his arme beene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed;
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:17566:74"/> 
               <hi>David</hi> grew (by his great ſinnings) into great lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhings; but the Lord ſent <hi>Nathan</hi> the Prophet unto him, and his faithfull dealing was a meanes of his happy renewing. What we pull downe by heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the voyce of ſinne, that may be built up againe by hearkening to the voyce of Gods ſpirit. But then this muſt thou doe, if ever thou wouldeſt be ſtrengthened, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Strive for a plain and pliable heart which may yeeld ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to whatſoever law or courſe the Lord ſhal direct thee unto by his word; if the word <note place="margin">As the Iewes in Ieremiah</note> offer thee a reſtoring plaiſter, but thou wilt not apply it, and
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:17566:74"/> preſcribe unto thee ſtrengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing methods, but thou wilt not follow them, now thy heart may grow more hardened, but thy graces will never be ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened.</p>
            <p>But this doe, ſtrive to yeeld up thy ſoule in an humble ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to the heavenly ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, that if they ſay forbeare, thy heart anſwers I will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare; if they ſay doe, thy heart anſwers, I deſire to doe thy will. Cooperate with the word received, when it hath got into thy ſoule, and ſtirred thee in any kinde, when thou percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt any healing vertue gone from Chriſt by it unto thee; oh bleſſe the Lord, and get home,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:17566:75"/> work it againe upon thy ſoule by holy meditation, yea and yet againe by holy petition.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> Thou muſt even doe in this kinde, as <hi>Benhadads</hi> ſervants did in another, they watched the words which fell from the King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and improved them, ſo muſt thou watch what motions the Lord puts into thy heart in private, and cheriſh them, watch what im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions the Lord makes upon thy ſpirit by his word, and not onely excite thy heart to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace them, but work them often and often upon thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and this is the way to make thy weake ſparke to grow unto a flame.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:17566:75"/>7 And laſtly, there muſt bee lively conſociation by a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall inſtinct, the weaker things doe cling and winde up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by the ſtronger, as the weake Ivie upon the ſtrong Oake: ſo thou muſt inwardly and affectionately joyne thy ſelfe with ſtrong and lively Chriſtians, who skill the waies of grace, and walke in them, who are good, and know how to doe good, who have hearts to pitty thee, heads to direct thee, and armes to beare thee up.</p>
            <p>Thou maieſt exceedingly be repaired by their heavenly wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in counſelling of thee, and kept in by their tender
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:17566:76"/> watchings over thee, and put forward by their daily exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of thee, and refreſhed by their ſeaſonable comfortings of thee, and led on by their ſtrict and lively examples, yea even ſtirred up by the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe bleſſed experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which thou perceiveſt in them, through a carefull com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God, as alſo much aſſiſted by the ſucceſſe of their prayers for thy particular condition.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the manner.</p>
            <p>Now be pleaſed to heare a little for the manner, how yee <note place="margin">5 <hi>Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular.</hi>
               </note> are to ſet upon this ſtrengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing work, and then I have done with this propoſition.</p>
            <pb n="137" facs="tcp:17566:76"/>
            <p>If thou findeſt thy ſelfe to be a weakened Chriſtian, then ſet upon thy ſtrengthening worke.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Preſently: <hi>Initia morborum cavenda,</hi> ſay the Phyſitians, and therefore their rule is, <hi>principiis obſta, &amp;c.</hi> we ſhould ſet upon diſeaſes, as ſoone as diſeaſes ſet upon us, not trifle away the methods of recovery: three things muſt be lookt into in time, tides, ſeaſons, diſeaſes.</p>
            <p>If wee preſently oppoſe our decayings,</p>
            <p>Firſt, we ſhall prevent the deadlineſſe of diſeaſes; hadſt thou oppoſed thy negligent, careleſſe ſpirit at the firſt, thou hadſt not now been bleeding
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:17566:77"/> under ſo many wounds, thou hadſt not ſtepped downe from one ſinne to another, thou hadſt not gone ſo deſperately from the Lord.</p>
            <p>Therefore watch thy heart, and often examine it, weekely, nay, daily; thy languiſhings are by this manner ſooner eſpied, and ſooner ſtaied.</p>
            <p>Secondly, our ſtrengthening will hereby become more eaſie; it is eaſier to fetch a man from the brink, then from the depth of the channell, and for a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian to cure a diſtemper, then to heale a diſeaſe.</p>
            <p>There is uſually in the firſt impairings, leſſe corruption, and more ſtrength of grace to
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:17566:77"/> oppoſe it and ſubdue it; Beleeve it, long decayings are the more uncomfortable and more diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult for recovery: Therefore if thou falleſt ſuddenly, riſe quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; remember one thing, it is a very dangerous thing to ſuffer the ſoule to habituate it ſelfe to decayings, all cuſtomes are hardly broken.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Voluntarily; it is true, that though thou decaieſt more and more, yet the Lord may awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken thee at length and recover thee, but doe not put the Lord to it. The Phyſitian may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps heale a deeply languiſhing patient, but it will coſt the pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent dearly and bitterly. <hi>Ioab</hi> got little by not comming to <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalom,</hi>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:17566:78"/> for he at length fetcht him by ſetting his corne on fire; if thou wilt not come in of thy owne accord, but ſtand it out, I tell thee the Lord will fetch thee in indeed, but he will ſend a whirlewinde after thee, as to <hi>Elijah,</hi> he will ſend flames in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy conſcience, if thou wilt needs put him upon compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſory waies.</p>
            <p>Nay, but rather peruſe thy decayings thy ſelfe, and arraign thy ſelfe and judge thy ſelfe, and afflict thy ſelfe, and hye thee to make thy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> peace, and to recover ſtrength; it argues the better heart to fall unwillingly; but willingly to riſe, hereby peace
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:17566:78"/> is ſooner made, and ſtrength ſooner reſtored.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Prudently, when a tree is withering, you need not poure buckets on every branch, if you water the roots, it is as if you watered all. There is an holy part in recovering our graces againe, if you can recover the roots, you have hit the way to renew all. Now there are two radicall graces (as it were) if they be ſtrengthened, all the reſt will come to be ſtrengthened, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 Faith, this is a root grace, and this is a ſtrengthening grace, it is of ſingular power with God, and with Chriſt, and with the ſpirit of God: It is that
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:17566:79"/> grace which laies hold on, and applies all our ſtrengthening helpes, ſo that it deales at the ſprings of ſtrength, and brings away ſtrength from them.</p>
            <p>But this is not all, faith is no ſooner ſtrengthened to lay hold on our ſtrength, but (like thoſe common officials in nature, the ſtomack, liver, heart, and brain) it imparts this vigour to all the new man: every grace gets when faith gets, the more a man can beleeve, the more will that man grieve for ſinne, the more will he feare to ſinne, the more will hee hate ſinne, the more will hee repent of ſinne, the more carefull will hee be to walke before God, the more
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:17566:79"/> tender and conſcientious will hee grow in duties, the more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble unto praier and the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and the more ſucceſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full under them.</p>
            <p>Therefore deale prudently for thy ſtrengthening: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> when an houſe is declining, we doe not meddle with every rafter and piece of wood; no, but wee ſtrengthen the pillers and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation; faith is the piller (as it were) of our graces; ſtrengthen it to more apprehenſion, appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, to more ſubmiſſion to the wil of God, to more affiance, to more dependance on God through the bloud of Chriſt, and faith, will both finde out thy ſtrength, and impart it. <hi>I
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:17566:80"/> can doe all things through Christ that ſtrengthens me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Love, this is another radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call grace, not that it brings forth other graces for their ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits, but onely that it eggeth on other graces to their acts and operations, for as holy love is a moſt active quality in it ſelfe, ſo it doth make the Chriſtian to be moſt active; it is a doing thing, and makes the perſon to be doing.</p>
            <p>More fully thus.</p>
            <p n="1">1 There is activity flowing from love; grace ſhall never be idle; where the love of God is ſtrong, the love of Chriſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraines <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.</note> me, ſaith Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> it is like the vertuous woman
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:17566:80"/> in the laſt of the <hi>Proverbs,</hi> who did ſet all her handmaids to employment, for love will finde duty enough, for it is never quiet but in doing the will of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2 There is diligence: It will not ſet graces to a naked work, but to a diligent worke, even carefully and diligently to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe their acts, to take all the ſeaſons of holy actings, ſtrictly to oppoſe and reſiſt corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, neatly to ſet out duties, ſo as God may have moſt glory.</p>
            <p n="3">3 There is delightfulneſſe, it makes our communion with God, pleaſant, and the works of piety eaſie to the ſoule: and the more delightfull and eaſie any acts are, the more frequent they
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:17566:81"/> grow; <hi>David</hi> loving of the Lord, was glad when they ſaid, let us goe unto the houſe of the Lord, and he had a deſire even to dwell and reſt there, as the birds did, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now put all this together, and you ſhall ſee that if love be ſtrengthened, all our ſpirituall eſtate will be ſtrengthened, for it makes our graces to be active and doing, to be carefull and exact in doing, to be delightfull and cheerefull in doing good, and in communion with God, and all theſe are admirable meanes to raiſe and ſtrengthen graces.</p>
            <p>Foraſmuch as the more any Chriſtian doth, the more hee
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:17566:81"/> may, by uſing his ſpirituall ſtrength, he alwaies increaſeth it, and alſo wit.</p>
            <p>All know, that diligence in acting is a thrifty courſe; <hi>the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent hand makes rich,</hi> ſaith <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> ſo the diligent Chriſtian is the gaining Chriſtian; and that delightfull frequency of acting, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> it is like the twiſting of a cord, which comes thereby to be the ſtronger: No Chriſtian is ſo able in the habits of grace, as hee who is conſcientiouſly frequent in the practiſe or exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of grace.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Seriouſly and in good ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, and not ſlightly and faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; the recovery of a faint ſoule will never be effected by faint
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:17566:82"/> workings: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> gentle phyſicke is improper for tough diſeaſes: you did fall into your decayed eſtate by remiſſive operations or act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and thinke you that what was not able to keep up your graces from ſinking, can now quicken and raiſe them, being greatly ſunke.</p>
            <p>If my hands cannot keep a ſwouning perſon from falling to the ground, can they lift him up being fallen? whereas every heavy body, the farther it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendeth, the heavier it is.</p>
            <p>No, no, Chriſtian thou decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt thy ſelfe, to thinke that a few complaints, or a few ſighes, or a few teares, or a pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er (once in a quarter of a yeere)
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:17566:82"/> more earneſtly preſſed, will ſerve the turne.</p>
            <p>I tell thee that thy wounds are deepe, and thy diſeaſes are ſtrong, thou art deeply revolted from the Lord, the very founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are ſhaken and battered within thy ſoule.</p>
            <p>What talkeſt thou of putting a ſoft cloth over thy ſtinking and feſtred wounds of ſinfull cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption; thou oughteſt to ſearch deeply, and to cut off the dead fleſh, leſt the whole be gangre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            <p>Take my adviſe, even breake up the fallow ground, I meane thy hollow heart, ſearch and try it to the utmoſt, not by ſlight, but by deep and full hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliations
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:17566:83"/> and ſupplications, make thy peace; not by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, but by extraordinary per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances ſeeke to renue thy ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Thy fals have beene great, and therefore thy worke muſt not be ſlight; great ſinnings require grand ſorrowings, and low fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, the more induſtry for higher riſings; therefore act thy ſtrengthening part with all thy ſtrength, and as it were for thy very life; remember that <hi>David</hi> was in faſting, and <hi>Peter</hi> in bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter teares for their falling, and ſo they roſe againe.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Throughly and to ſome purpoſe; doe not begin a ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thening worke, and then either
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:17566:83"/> upon the motions of a laſie heart, or a fearefull heart, or an unbeleeving heart, be diſcoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and deſiſt: this inconſtancy would keepe thee in an everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting infirmity, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> juſt as if a Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſhould follow the preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Phyſitian for a day or two, but afterwards finding that to be ſomewhat painefull and troubleſome, hee will bee bound no longer, but then hee fals ill againe. So if thou ſet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the waies of ſtrengthening, and a while thou wilt keepe cloſe to praying and hearing, and humbling, and reforming, but perceiving the workes to be painefull and offenſive to thy corrupt heart, and too ſtrict to
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:17566:84"/> thy licentious heart, or the fruits of them to be hopeleſſe to thy unbeleeving heart, (I cannot hold out, all is in vaine, or to little purpoſe) I tell thee that thou doeſt but play the foole with thy ſoule, ſet it forward and backward; this were to twiſt and untwiſt <hi>Penelopes</hi> threed; thou never wilt get any thing by an inconſtant and weary ſpirit.</p>
            <p>But this muſt thou doe, if thou wouldeſt recover thy ſtrength indeed, thou muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver admit of interruptions, thou muſt never break off thy renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing worke, till thou haſt got to thy former ſtation in grace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</p>
            <pb n="153" facs="tcp:17566:84"/>
            <p>The worke muſt bee a daily worke, a conſtant going on in mourning, praying, &amp;c. till thou haſt got thy tender conſcience againe, till thou haſt gotten thy broken heart againe, till thou haſt got thy more willingly and cheerefully obedient heart a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, till thou haſt recovered thy firſt love; and canſt doe thy firſt works againe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>It is true, thou ſhalt meet with many temptations from Satan, with many contrary ſuggeſtions from thine owne ſpirit, and with many diſcouragements from the world, and it is true alſo that thy doings may not at every time equall or be like to it ſelfe; thou mayeſt feele thy phyſicke at one time to worke better
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:17566:85"/> then at another; ſometimes thou mayeſt doe thy ſtrengthening worke with more ſtrength, ſometimes with leſse; ſometimes with more liberty of ſpirit, ſometimes with leſse, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times with more comfort, ſometime with leſse.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> Yet let nothing diſcourage thee, or take off thy ſpirit from the worke, but follow on to know the Lord and his ſtrength, againſt all temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, againſt all ſuggeſtions, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all diſcouragements, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all thine owne feares and feelings, and inequality of ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, yet give not over; but,</p>
            <p>Keep up thy ſervices ſtill, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain frequent communion with God ſtill, be begging ſtill for the
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:17566:85"/> ſtrength of Ieſus Chriſt to raiſe thee, heare ſtill, uſe the preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions till health comes, thou art in the way, and muſt not reſt till thou haſt obtained.</p>
            <p>If thou breakeſt off before thou haſt regained thy ſtrength, thou wilt fall backe againe, and alſo loſe all thy new endeavours for thy recovery in grace.</p>
            <p>Thus much for the ſecond propoſition, I proceed now to the third, of which I can but give a touch, leſt I be hindred in the proſecution of the matter in the next verſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I have not found thy works per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the eſtate though viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly <note place="margin">Thirdly.</note> faire to the eyes of men, yet
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:17566:86"/> it may be really imperfect in the eyes of God. Amongſt the Churches, <hi>Sardis</hi> had a name that it lived, but with God it had not that name and eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Wee Chriſtians have the judgement of charity, but God hath the judgement of infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity: we looke onely on the skin and ſurface of actions, but God looks into the hearts and ſpirits of perſons: wee judge of the heart by the actions, but God judgeth of our eſtates by the heart.</p>
            <p>Now the outward acts (up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſeverall arguments, and for ſeverall ends and inducements, may be extreamely different
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:17566:86"/> from the inward habit and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition. Perſons for their cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dits ſake, and for their peculiar advantages, may draw out acts naturally good, when yet their ſpirits ſtand not right, either for principles or ends of thoſe acts: ſo that notwithſtanding al their profeſſion, their eſtate may bee imperfect before God: partly,</p>
            <p>For the frame and conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſoule,</p>
            <p>For the vigour and fulneſſe of acting.</p>
            <p>For the ſcope and intentions in performing.</p>
            <p>For the mixtures in matters of faith or converſation.</p>
            <p>But I cannot now inlarge in this ſingular affection.</p>
            <pb n="158" facs="tcp:17566:87"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>1</label> Onely it may teach us above all, to looke unto our ſpirituals, as they abide in, and flow from our hearts and ſoules, upon which principally the Lord lookes: he ſearcheth the hearts and reynes, and approveth the actings of the heart, more then of the hand, and therefore wee reade, that he had firſt reſpect unto <hi>Abel,</hi> and then unto his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering.</p>
            <p>2 To ſtudy Gods approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on more than mans; it is not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient nor ſafe, that either wee alone judge our eſtates to bee good, or that men judge them to be ſo, unleſſe the Lord findes them to be ſo: every Chriſtian is that as God judgeth him to
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:17566:87"/> be, and he ſtands or fals accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this righteous judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the al-ſeeing, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowing God. And ſo I take leave of that verſe, and proceed to the next.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Remember therefore how thou</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Revel.</hi> 3. 3.</note> 
               <hi>haſt received, and heard, and hold faſt, and repent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In theſe words you have the other branches of the ſpirits ſpeciall directions to the Church of <hi>Sardis,</hi> which are three, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Remembrance, <hi>(remember</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Three branches.</note> 
                  <hi>therefore how thou hast received and heard,)</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 Perſiſtence, <hi>(and hold faſt,)</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 Renewed repentance, <hi>(and repent.)</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb n="160" facs="tcp:17566:88"/>
            <p>Briefly to open the words.</p>
            <p>Remember) ſometimes the word is taken for the act of a particular faculty of the ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſoule, which is called by the Philoſophers, <hi>Reminiſcentia,</hi> and then it is the calling backe of a thing, or object formerly knowne and laid up in the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory.</p>
            <p>Sometimes it is taken for the act of ſerious conſideration appertaining to the judicious faculty of the ſoule, wherein apprehended truths are well weighed, throughly thought on or conſidered of, in both re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects I conjecture, it may bee taken in this place</p>
            <p>How) ſome reade that word
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:17566:88"/> rather thus, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> what, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. <hi>i.</hi> call to minde and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what thou haſt received and heard, as if it were a word declaring the matter, but rather in this place it imports the manner, and therefore it is well tranſlated, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, How, noting the manner how Chriſt taught, and preſcribed them at the firſt, and alſo the manner how they embraced thoſe holy rules of his for doctrine &amp; converſation</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou haſt received and heard,)</hi> that is, aſſented unto, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced thoſe truths and directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Chriſt, where is expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: firſt, their ancient ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or embracing of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt <hi>(received,)</hi> and ſecondly, the meanes
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:17566:89"/> or way thereof, <hi>viz.</hi> by hearing, <hi>(and heard)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot poſſibly with any profit inſiſt on all the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles out of theſe and the other words, conſidering that little part of time which remaines for me to worke amongſt you, only I will point at three ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar propoſitions, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1 That holy truths once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, <note place="margin">Three propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note> are often to be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred and thought on, <hi>(Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, &amp;c.)</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 That acceptance of truths is not enough, but Chriſtians muſt adde thereto a perſiſtence in truths, <hi>(hold faſt)</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 That renewed repentance is required of Chriſtians, as well
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:17566:89"/> as initiall <hi>(and repent.)</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>You ſee that all theſe propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions naturally flow from the text, and are very proper for us, and for the occaſion upon which they are handled, I begin with the firſt of them, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> That holy truths once recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, are often to be remembred and thought on.</p>
            <p>There are three things which ſhould fall into a fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent conſideration:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Our former ſinnes, and this will keepe us humble.</item>
               <item>2 Gods former mercies, and this will make us thankfull.</item>
               <item>3 Received truths, and this will make us dutifull and fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="164" facs="tcp:17566:90"/>
            <p>The Iewes were to binde them as frontlets between their eyes, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. 8. to which <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> alludes in <hi>Pro. 6. 21. binde</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut. 6. 8. Pro.</hi> 6. 21.</note> 
               <hi>them continually upon thy heart, and tye them about thy necke,</hi> and <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. 12. 11. they are to be as nailes</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12. 11.</note> 
               <hi>faſtened.</hi> Looke on <hi>David,</hi> and this was his practiſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal</hi> 119 15.</note> 
               <hi>I will meditate in thy ſtatutes,</hi> there once, then reade verſe 23. <hi>thy ſervant did meditate in thy ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes,</hi> there is the ſecond time, but then reade verſe 48. <hi>I will meditate in thy statutes,</hi> there is the third time; what ſpeake I of once or twice, or thrice; ſee him in verſe 97. <hi>Oh how I love thy law, it is my meditation all the day.</hi> The Apoſtles are frequent
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:17566:90"/> in their exhortations to this purpoſe, to remember, to lay up, to keepe in minde, not to forget the holy doctrines deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by them, nay, and Chriſt preſſed the ſame alſo upon themſelves upon many occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. But for the cleere opening of this propoſition, premiſe with me theſe particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The frequent remembring of former truths muſt be a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance by way of ſubie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and not by way of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction; we muſt not remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber them and queſtion them, much leſſe abuſe and pervert them, leaſt of all oppoſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe them.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The remembrance muſt
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:17566:91"/> be ingenuous, and not preiudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall; though we muſt ſticke to, yet not in the truths received, our former remembrance, muſt not contract a preſent or future neglect of any other truths which God ſhall reveale unto us, as when many remember the Sermons of dead men, and ſlight the diſcoveries of the living.</p>
            <p n="3">3 There is a threefold re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of former truths.</p>
            <p>One is notionall, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> which is like the often looking into a glaſſe, or when a perſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds truths as hee doth pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, gaze on them, and that is all.</p>
            <p>Another is verball, when a
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:17566:91"/> perſon renues his acquaintance and complements with truth onely: his memory onely loades his tongue, like a naked Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomer who knowes heaven, and can onely talke of it.</p>
            <p>A third is practicall, when the remembrance is like a cloud deſcending on the plants,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> or like a fire felt as well as ſeene, this kinde of remembrance hath three degrees in it, for it is partly,</p>
            <p>Directive, when truths re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred are made a compaſſe for us to ſayle by, or copies for us to write after, ſtill teaching and guiding us how to draw the lines and letters of our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation.</p>
            <pb n="168" facs="tcp:17566:92"/>
            <p>Affective, when truths re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred are like the confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Chriſt (riſing from the dead) burning and inflaming of our hearts with moſt affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionate love unto them.</p>
            <p>Effective, when truths re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, are truths obeyed; we often conſider former do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, and ſtill better our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent converſations.</p>
            <p>After this practicall forme, are wee to remember received truths.</p>
            <p>4 There is,</p>
            <p n="1">1 A materiall remembrance, which is partly of the things themſelves, partly of the reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of them, partly of the manner and meanes of revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="169" facs="tcp:17566:92"/>2 Formall remembrance of <note place="margin">For the manner, five waies.</note> truths received, which is rather of the manner how wee our ſelves did receive them; we are often to thinke on truths recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, not onely as they ſtand in propoſition or revelation, but alſo how they ſtood with us when wee did receive them for energy or operation: and thus I conjecture we are to remember truths received.</p>
            <p n="1">1 With what eſtimations and admirations wee did receive them; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> like thoſe people who have the Sunne but halfe the yeere, they run after it, and are ready to adore it in its approch; ſo when we did receive holy truths at the firſt, we received
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:17566:93"/> them as the very oracles of God, not as the words of man, but as they are indeed, the words of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2 With what ſubjection of ſpirit we did receive them, wee did not onely admire their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency, but felt their efficacie; the word came not in word onely, but in power and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity over our very conſciences, and this power was a full pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and an eaſie power, the truths which wee received, did command and awe, and order our whole man, and wee too were moſt willing to reſigne up our ſelves to the obedience of the Goſpell in all things, and to be caſt into that mould of
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:17566:93"/> heavenly doctrine.</p>
            <p n="3">3 With what affections wee did receive them; O then, thoſe conflictings of ſpirit, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 32 <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 32.</note> thoſe bathes of griefe and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly compunction with them, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 37. thoſe flames <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 37.</note> of love, with thoſe Chriſtians, <hi>Acts</hi> 4. 32. thoſe raptures of joy <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts 4. 32. Acts</hi> 16.</note> with <hi>Lydia, Acts</hi> 16. yea thoſe extenſions of zeale with the Galathians to Saint <hi>Paul, Gal.</hi> 4.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.</note> the word had a ſurpaſſing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence upon all our affections, to melt, and convert, to raiſe, and diſpoſe of them.</p>
            <p n="4">4 With what reſolute loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſo that we did hate and defie all contrary errors and waies, and ſo were our hearts ſworne
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:17566:94"/> to divine truths, and (as it were) eſpouſed to them, that wee once reſolved to live and dye in thoſe truths, and for thoſe truths, wee could not endure any mixture with them, nor heare of any divorce from them.</p>
            <p n="5">5 With what reverence wee did embrace the Ambaſſadors of heavenly truths, they were as the Angels of God to us, &amp; we were like (almoſt) with <hi>Corneli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> to adore the <hi>Peters</hi> and <hi>Pauls,</hi> I meane the miniſters of God revealing his truths unto us; the feet of them who brought unto us the glad tidings of our ſalvation, were beautifull and moſt acceptable unto us.</p>
            <pb n="173" facs="tcp:17566:94"/>
            <p>Now here are two queſtions briefly to be reſolved.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>What truths heard and received, we are often to conſider and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> To this I anſwer. </p>
            <p n="1">1 There muſt be an endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to remember all the truths, as Chriſt ſaid of the fragments, gather them up, and let none be loſt; ſo it muſt bee ſaid of holy truths (on which the ſoule hath formerly fed) ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther them up all, let none be loſt.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> You ſee that the Goldſmith doth not onely looke after the maſſie piece of gold, but he carefully lookes after every ray and duſt of gold, and preſerves it.</p>
            <pb n="174" facs="tcp:17566:95"/>
            <p>Every truth of God is preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, it is more precious then gold; it is excellent, and as it is excellent in it ſelfe, ſo it may be uſefull to us,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> there is not a ſtar in heaven, but is of ſome good to the lower world; ſo there is not one truth of God, but may be of ſome good uſe to a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</p>
            <p>But if either for the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of truths, or the ſublimity of truths, or for the obſcure manner of diſcovering theſe truths, or for the impotency and irretentiveneſſe of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding and unclaſping memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or for the ſpace of time, ſince truths were delivered and received; it ſo fals out, that all
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:17566:95"/> heard and once received truths will not ſtand upon record, into which they have beene entred, but are in many places defaced and cancelled,</p>
            <p n="2">2 There muſt at leaſt bee a faithfull remembrance of the moſt neceſſary and chiefe truths, namely of thoſe which more immediately and inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mately, and unauoydably con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern our ſalvation, of the which (for methods ſake) I conjecture there may be three heads, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 That vitall truth concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Chriſt and faith in him, this is the great fundamentall truth.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>
               </label> 2 That vivificall truth concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning repentance in the conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:17566:96"/> of the heart from dead workes.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That practicall truth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning obedience, in ordering the life and courſe of a conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted perſon.</p>
            <p>As the moraliſts ſay of Fame, or of a mans good name, <hi>Omnia ſi perdas, famam ſervare memento. Qua ſemel amiſsâ poſtea nullus eris. (i)</hi> whatſoever com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity you loſe, be ſure yet to preſerve that iewell of a good name. That is ſo choyce a iewell, that whatſoever a man loſeth, hee muſt yet take heed and care of that. The ſame may bee ſaid of theſe forenamed truths; though through ſome defect, or frailty, or malignity,
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:17566:96"/> any other hiſtoricall or proble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall truths may ſlip from us, yet theſe muſt be written in our hearts with the point of a Diamond, and as in marble, the characters of them are to bee kept freſh and alive, and are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to be blotted out.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>And why this faithfull and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent remembrance, or renewed conſideration of truths heard and received?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> Reaſons thereof many. </p>
            <p>1 Though ſometimes an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent may be ſufficient to a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular word of truth for the preſent, yet the vertue and uſe of that may be for the future.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> It is with truths as it is with treaſuries, whereinto much gold
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:17566:97"/> or ſiluer is put and kept ſafe; a little whereof my ſerve for the time being, but moſt or all of it may be brought out upon fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and ſeverall occaſions.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> Or as it is with friends and garments, which though wee doe not uſe every one of them every day, yet ere we dye, wee may have an uſefull occaſion for them all.</p>
            <p>The truths which thou haſt heard from the word ten yeeres agoe, may ſerve thee twenty yeeres hence; that diſcovery of the mercy of God, of the bloud of Chriſt, of the freeneſſe of grace, &amp;c. theſe may be of great availe unto thee, and of ſweet and proper helpe unto thee
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:17566:97"/> when thou commeſt to old age, or to a dying bed.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> It is not with truths heard and received, as with our meat eaten and digeſted, the vertue of which may bee gone in few daies, but as it is with a leaſe, for life, which this yeere brings in our revenue, and ſo it doth the next yeere, &amp;c. ſo divine truths may yeeld unto thee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent comfort and ſtrength, yea, and they can, being rightly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced, be the ſtaffe in thy hand to morrow to ſupport thee, and the river in thy conſcience to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh thee; that heavenly truth which was thy ſtarre at this time, may fitly upon occaſions, ſerve to bee thy guide at any
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:17566:98"/> time, as the ſtarre to the wiſe men, which appeared the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Frequent remembrance of divine truths is (as it were) a ſpurre to further obedience, and therefore Saint <hi>Peter</hi> joynes, <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 13.</note> putting in remembrance, and ſtirring up, as if then we ſhould revive our ſervices, when wee did renue our memories.</p>
            <p>Every truth newly and ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly thought on, is as it were a ſecond Sermon or repetition, and inculcating of it upon our hearts; I am ſure it is like a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther digeſtion, which ſerves for the better health and ſtrength of our bodies.</p>
            <p n="3">3 It is a meanes much to
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:17566:98"/> ſtrengthen our graces; the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers have a ſaying, <hi>eodem nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimur ex quo generamur,</hi> that wee are nouriſhed by that of which wee are generated; the truths of God begat our graces, and the ſame truths well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred and peruſed, will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe them.</p>
            <p>Thoſe promiſes which here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore inclined thy heart, and perſwaded it to beleeve, can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually beare and raiſe up thy heart to ſtronger degrees of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe: as Chriſt when he would helpe his diſciples againſt a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular infidelity, objected unto them, <hi>why doe ye not remember?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark.</hi> 8. 18.</note> intimating that a right remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring of his works, would have
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:17566:99"/> inabled them much againſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beliefe.</p>
            <p>And ſo doth the remembrance of the words of Chriſt, of his truths, which are as able to build us up in grace, as to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate it unto us.</p>
            <p n="4">4 It is a revocation from ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, as <hi>David</hi> ſaid, I conſidered my waies, and turned my feet unto thy teſtimonies; the ſame may be ſaid of holy truths; a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring conſideration of them is a recovering of an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and falling ſoule. Saint <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> forgate his Maſter, and then forgate himſelfe, he forgate the words of a Maſter, and then the duty of a ſervant, but <hi>Peter</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered himſelfe againe: and
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:17566:99"/> how did he ſo? the text ſaith that hee remembred the words of Ieſus, and when hee had thought thereon, hee went out and wept bitterly.</p>
            <p n="5">5 It is an avocation or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdment from errours; why doe men ſo commonly ſlip into new errors? one maine cauſe is, they have let ſlip old truths, they have loſt their touch-ſtone to try doctrine by, they doe not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what and how they have heard and received, and therfore they deſtroy what they themſelves have built.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> Like a ſhip which hath loſt her anchor, toſſed with waves and windes every way, ſo they are hurried and puffed up and
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:17566:100"/> downe with every winde of doctrine.</p>
            <p>But he who rightly remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers the truth, hath not onely thereby a touch-ſtone to try and diſcover contrary errours, but likewiſe a buckler to ſecure his judgement, and a ſword to cut off the corrupt reaſonings and fallacies of the gaine-ſayer.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Laſtly, it is of ſingular good, and concernement to a diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and deſerted ſoule, and to a debarred perſon.</p>
            <p>The daies of famine may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall thee, and then the food which <hi>Ioſeph</hi> laid up, may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve thee, if future meanes ſhould faile, will not former and remembred truths be of
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:17566:100"/> comfort? and are you ſure that ſeaſons will laſt for ever? where is <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> who did not know her day of peace? and where are the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia?</hi> or the daies of ſickneſſe may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall thee, wherein thou art de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barred of the market, I meane, the publike aſſembly of the Saints, and art ſo weakened, that reade at all thou canſt not; if now thy ſoule can remember God, and remember the truths of God, and can ſecretly confer with them, they may be of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed helpe and peace unto thee; yea, the daies of deſertion may befall thee, the Lord may not looke on thee as formerly; hee may not confer at all with thee
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:17566:101"/> in ſenſe and feeling: and what refuge haſt thou now, but to flye to the truths of God, through which thou didſt here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore heare him and perceive him, and this may prove a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and ſolace to thy heart.</p>
            <p>Sure I am, <hi>Aſaph</hi> in his deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions did ſo, ſee him in <hi>Pſal. 77. 10. I will remember the yeeres of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77. 10.</note> 
               <hi>the right hand of the moſt high; I will remember the workes of the Lord, ſurely I will remember thy wonders of old:</hi> former embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are new encouragements.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> Thus for the explication and confirmation of the point, I now come to the application of it to our ſelves.</p>
            <p>Should received truths be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred?
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:17566:101"/> then,</p>
            <p n="1">1 Hearing is not all, ſome there are who heare not at all, they are like the deafe Adders which refuſe to heare the voice of the charmer: Chriſt is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſpeake, but they are not pleaſed to hearken: how much have theſe to anſwer for? O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers doe heare, and that is all; the word is but as a naturall ſound to excite that naturall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie of hearing, but they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not what they heare: the word preached is as a book ſealed up unto them, they think it enough to come to Church, &amp;c. Others doe heare and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the truths delivered, but then they minde them no
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:17566:102"/> more, they leave all at the Church doore, as wee doe our friends at the grave, forgetting that we came to a feaſt, to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry away, and not to a grave to leave all behinde, as if the word were a tale, or a dreame, it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly forgotten; in comes the world, out goes the word, to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular buſineſſes, or ſinfull acts, they preſently apply themſelves, and ſo is the word <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> ſqueized out like water out of a ſpunge, or the characters of it glide away like the impreſſions of a Seale upon the ſlippery water.</p>
            <p>Perhaps many a thouſand Sermon they have heard in their daies (and would thinke it a mortall fault) not to heare, but
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:17566:102"/> for meditating, pondering, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viewing of delivered truths, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them to minde, the better to order their hearts and lives, they will not trouble them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo farre; as if truth were a burden, or an unworthy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion.</p>
            <p>Now to the forgetfull hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, I would commend theſe things to be conſidered of.</p>
            <p n="1">1 If his forgetfulneſſe bee onely of good things (when yet in any other thing and buſineſſe his remembrance is quicke enough, he can remember a tale or ſtory twenty yeeres ſince) it is a very uncomfortable ſigne.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe that every good mans memory is not an equall
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:17566:103"/> treaſurie, nor perhaps a very fruitfull ſoyle, but to have a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory like an utterly barren wombe, retentive of no ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all truths, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> but like ſand in a glaſſe, put in the one part, and inſtantly running our to the other, this totall and abſolute falſeneſſe in our memories, is a ſhrewd preſumption that either wee doe not at all rightly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of, and underſtand ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall truths, or if wee doe, yet that we doe not much care for them and reſpect them.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Forgetfulneſſe of truths heard and received, is a kinde of very evill ignorance; the School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men doe diſtinguiſh of <hi>Ignoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae purae negationis,</hi> wherein a
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:17566:103"/> man doth not know, and of <hi>Ignorantiae pravae diſpoſitionis,</hi> wherein either a man will not, or unfits himſelfe to know. Thus is it with forgetfulneſſe, truths forgotten are like truths unknowne, and the more that the knowledge of former truths weare out, the leſſe capacity is there to apprehend and receive further truths:</p>
            <p>Nor is this all, forgetfulneſſe is not onely a curtaine drawne over knowledge, but it is a bar alſo to our practiſe: the forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 1. 22.</note> hearer can be no good pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitioner.</p>
            <p>For no man acceptably pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſeth more then hee knowes, and no man properly knowes
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:17566:104"/> more then he remembers.</p>
            <p>Nor is that all, forgetfulneſſe keeps us not only in an eſtate of ignorance and blindeneſſe, nor onely in an eſtate of barrenneſſe and undoingneſſe, but further yet, it keepes us in a condition of ſadneſſe and uncomfortable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; for all our comforts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon divine truths (they are our ſprings of joy) but with this caution, ſo farre as they are ſolidly and rightly applied by us (<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> as ſtrong waters refreſheth when they are taken) now the forgetting perſon, is an unap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying perſon, there can be no good uſing, where there is no good remembring of holy truths,</p>
            <pb n="193" facs="tcp:17566:104"/>
            <p>So that now by thy forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, divine truths are loſt, and the operations of them are loſt, they can neither guide thee nor helpe thee, nor preſerve or comfort thee at all; and if all theſe be loſt, thou thy ſelfe canſt not be ſafe; whatſoever opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thou wilt have of thy ſelfe, Saint <hi>Iames</hi> aſſures thee that thou deceiveſt thine own ſelfe, <hi>cap.</hi> 1. 22. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 1. 22.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 If remembring of truths heard and received be neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, then be pleaſed to act the point which Chriſt here char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth, <hi>Remember how thou haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and heard:</hi> thou haſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps heard of the doctrine of ſinne, and knowledge thereof
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:17566:105"/> by the law, out of <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 7.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt heard of the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold aggravations of ſinne in ſeverall texts, as againſt know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, meanes of grace, mercies, afflictions, covenants, &amp;c. and of infidelity (that binding ſin) out of <hi>John</hi> 3. Thou haſt heard many a Sermon of the power of the word, for conviction and converſion, and for conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and for converſation, and for ſalvation, out of 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt heard of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediments of the ſoule from comming to Chriſt, partly from the love of ſinne, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. partly from the love of the world, <hi>Mark.</hi> 10. 22. partly
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:17566:105"/> from the perverſeneſſe of our wils, <hi>Math.</hi> 23. 37.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt heard of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations of the ſoule unto Chriſt, and much of the new covenant, out of <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. 1.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt heard much of faith, for the nature of it, out of <hi>Acts</hi> 16. for the degrees of it, out of <hi>Mark.</hi> 9. for the uſe of it in all the promiſes, out of 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. and of our love to God, out of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31. 23.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt heard the doctrine of repentance from dead works largely opened, out of <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 30. and further unfolded in the converſion of the Prodigall, out of <hi>Luke</hi> 15. and of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of temptations, out of
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:17566:106"/> 
               <hi>Luke</hi> 4. the kindes of them, and methods of defence and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt lately heard of that comfortable, ample, perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall care and goodneſſe of Gods providence over his Church and people out of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23. all over.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, thou haſt heard ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of a languiſhing, and of a recovering ſoule from this, out of <hi>Revel.</hi> 3. 2.</p>
            <p>I call God to record at this day, that (according to my knowledge and ability) I have, (as Saint <hi>Paul, Acts 20. 27.) not ſhunned to declare unto you all the counſell of God requiſite to your ſalvation, teſtifying unto you all,
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:17566:106"/> repentance towards God, and faith towards our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, verſe 21. yea in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, in ſtrength, in weakeneſse, in publike, in private, have I deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and endevoured your everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let not theſe pious truths ſlip from you, or be as water ſpilt upon the ground: Miniſters dye, but let not truths dye; Miniſters depart, but let not truths depart; ſtony hearts are bad, but iron memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries are good: if ye have heard truths and received them, why, ſtill retaine the truths for the truths ſake; let them ever abide with you, live with you, dye with you: And doe not locke
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:17566:107"/> up the truths onely, but let your memories faithfully ſerve out thoſe truths, according to your particular occaſions and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences of your life; hold them out to keep out errors, bring them out to keep up gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, improve the directions of the word, to leade your waies, and the comforts of the word to refreſh and encourage your hearts, and that you may skill the art of heavenly memory, know that,</p>
            <p>There are ſixe things which <note place="margin">Sixe things.</note> will much availe to helpe and inable the remembrance of truths heard and received.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Ardent affection: love is a ſafe locke, and a ready hand;
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:17566:107"/> which we much like, we ſhall much minde, <hi>David</hi> was fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent in love, and therefore fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent in thinking of Gods law, <hi>Pſal. 119. Oh how I love thy law!</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119 97.</note> 
               <hi>it is my meditation all the day:</hi> here was great love and great ſtudy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> a childe will not forget his mother.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Frequent meditation: ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny earthly things weare out by handling (as characters in gold or ſilver) but heavenly chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters abide longeſt where they are moſt peruſed. Every new and ſerious contemplation of them, makes a fairer and firmer impreſſion; it is like a ſecond ſtamping of them. The memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is like a glaſſe, and the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:17566:108"/> as an eye looking back into it: the more frequent ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance and familiarity that the underſtanding hath, by reflecting on the memory, the more ſtrongly are things ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in our remembrance.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Conſtant operation: if memory were more uſed, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory would be more uſefull: when thou haſt heard a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and art at home, then call thy memory to an account, how it hath played the faithfull ſteward for thee, what truth it hath remembred, by a daily ſtriving to remember, you ſhall daily perfect the remembrance.</p>
            <p n="4">4 A diſtinct apprehenſion: <hi>Saul</hi> was not eaſily found in the
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:17566:108"/> ſtuffe, and confuſed mindes are ſeldome linked with exact me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories; the more orderly and exact that the underſtanding is, the more eaſie is the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of things.</p>
            <p>Take heed of ignorant mindes that know not truths, and of confuſed mindes that can miſtake truths.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Abundant conference: this courſe <hi>Moſes</hi> preſcribed the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> to remember the lawes given unto them, <hi>viz</hi> that they ſhould often talke of them to their children; conference is as the driving in of the naile; one remembers that which the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forgets; our memories helpe our lips, and our lips doe
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:17566:109"/> ſtrengthen our memories.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Diligent practiſe: the ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler by a daily writing after the copy, doth thereby mend his hand, and helpe his memory. Truths are ordained for pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe; It cannot be, but that truths ſhould remaine faithfull in the memory, which are made faithfull in our walking. Truths eaſily take their leave of them who oppoſe them, or do not act them.</p>
            <p>Now to the ſecond aſſertion, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That acceptance of truths is <note place="margin">Second.</note> not ſufficient, but there muſt be perſiſtence in them <hi>(and hold faſt)</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſerva,</hi> or as <hi>Beza</hi> tranſlates it, <hi>obſerva.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="203" facs="tcp:17566:109"/>
            <p>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> is much in this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; <hi>hold faſt the forme of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim. 1. 13. Titus</hi> 1. 9.</note> 
               <hi>ſound words, 2 Tim.</hi> 1. 13. ſo again to <hi>Titus 1. 9. hold fast the faithfull word;</hi> and that this doctrine may not be thought proper and peculiar to the Preacher of the truth; but common to all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, hee therefore enlargeth the precept to all the <hi>Romans,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 9.</note> (and under them to all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians) to adhere or cleave unto what is good; the word in the originall is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that they ſhould bee glued unto it. <hi>Salomon</hi> in effect delivers the ſame <hi>Pro. 23. 23. Buy the truth and ſel. it not,</hi> a man may lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſell his houſe and lands as the Apoſtles did, and followed
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:17566:110"/> Chriſt, and in ſome ſenſe his wife and children, (as Saint <hi>Ierome in epiſt. ad Heliod.</hi> would rather then hee would put off Chriſt) yea and his owne life too, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> did, not count <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 21. 13.</note> it deare for Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But the truth muſt not bee ſold, it muſt be kept as a thing exceeding all price and bargain. Now for the fuller underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this propoſition, premiſe with me theſe particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1 That I ſpeake not of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane and morall truths, ſuch as are the rules in ſecular arts, in which there may bee and is many times, an infallibility; but of religious and divine truths, which are contained in the
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:17566:110"/> word of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Religious truths are ſo, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the imagination of man, or in the reality of the thing: I am not bound to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace, much leſſe to perſiſt in all which every man pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds for truths, or which he conjectures to be ſo; onely I am to hold faſt thoſe truths, which the word (rightly and genuine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expounded) teacheth and determineth to be ſo.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Againe, the truths which ſeeme to owne themſelves on the word of God, are either immediate and expreſſe, or one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mediate and deduced; expreſſe truths are to be held faſt, but deduced truths which are
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:17566:111"/> thence collected by the <hi>medium</hi> of a mans ability to judge, theſe are to bee tried and examined by the prime and immediate truths, and ſo far to be held as they are found (upon due ſearch) to have conformity with the immediate &amp; expreſſe rules of truth.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Expreſſe truths (ſuppoſe them to be knowne and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) may be conſidered either in the latitude of them, or with reſtriction; we may not thinke it ſufficient to hold faſt ſome particular truths, either the greater or the leſſer, and leave the reſt to ſhift for themſelves. But all knowne truths, even thoſe which are not of that
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:17566:111"/> maine concernement, not any one of them muſt be forſaken or left, but retained and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained: as <hi>Athanaſius</hi> and others of the firſt Nicene Fathers would not diminiſh, or adde one iota &amp; title about the deity of Chriſt; or as <hi>Moſes</hi> would not leave one hoofe behinde, ſo we muſt not renounce or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake any one branch of known truth, ſeeme it never ſo little in the eyes of men.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Though there be a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of times, yet there ought to bee no difference of holy truths; there are times of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity for the Goſpell, as <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantines</hi> time was to the Church, and there are times of
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:17566:112"/> calamity as <hi>Neroes</hi> time, and <hi>Diocleſians,</hi> and others the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting Emperours.</p>
            <p>Truth muſt be held faſt; yea all truth, at all times; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> you ſee that the ſtars doe ſhine in the coldeſt night of winter, as well as in the calmeſt night of ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; ſo truths muſt be held in the worſt as well as in the beſt daies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ioſephus</hi> reports of the Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritanes, that if any good and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour befell the Iewes, then they would pretend affinity and kindred with them, they came from <hi>Iacob;</hi> but if any calamity, then they were none of the ſtocke of <hi>Abraham.</hi> It muſt not be thus with us, to vary our
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:17566:112"/> hearty reſpect to truths accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the favour or diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement that the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtows upon them: but to cleave unto them as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> did, under the ſword, as S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> among the wilde beaſts, and <hi>Laurentius</hi> on the Gridiron, and <hi>Daniel</hi> among the Lyons, and the three children in the fiery furnace.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Sixthly, though there be a difference of perſons, yet wee muſt not differ and wave our reſpects to holy truths; perhaps thoſe holy truths which thou haſt heard and tryed, and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, may bee contradicted and diſputed, by ſome bold ſchiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall, hereticall braines, who
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:17566:113"/> would bleare and blur the truth, that ſo they may bring in dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable doctrines; by theſe they may be diſgraced, derided, and reproched, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> theſe dogs may bark againſt the moone and its light; yea or perhaps though they have forwardly courted &amp; profeſſed the truths, yet they may fall off with <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Philetus,</hi> and turne vile apoſtates.</p>
            <p>But as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid of Chriſt, that thou muſt ſay and act too, of truth, Though all men ſhould forſake thee, yet I will never forſake thee. Againſt all ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of diſputes, variety of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſchiſme and malice of evill men, and inconſtancy of ſome men, thou muſt be rightly
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:17566:113"/> ballanced. <hi>Hold faſt the truth which thou haſt heard and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>But how muſt truths be held faſt?</hi> 
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> In foure reſpects:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 In the judgement and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding.</item>
               <item>2 In the will and affection.</item>
               <item>3 In profeſſion.</item>
               <item>4 In converſation and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1 In the judgement: for aſſent and approbation; there muſt be a firme evidence of them. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that there is a latitude in our credence, upon more and more evidence of truth; there may be a further and ſtronger aſſent unto them, and approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them. But there muſt be
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:17566:114"/> no wavering in the judgement; we muſt not admit of a ſtagge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and reeling minde, nor of a levity in our judgements, to be driven and carried about with every winde of doctrine, as the Apoſtle ſpeakes, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 14. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Athanaſius</hi> knew this well, when he held his iudgement faſt in the truth of the deity of Chriſt, againſt the Arians: ſo Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin,</hi> his iudgement faſt in the doctrine of grace againſt the Pelagians, and <hi>Cyprian</hi> againſt the Donatiſts, or Novatians, or Cathariſts.</p>
            <p>It is an honour for a man to recant an errour, but a perfidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſhame for any Chriſtian to ſuffer any truth to be ſupplanted
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:17566:114"/> by any errour.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In the will and affection, our love muſt hold the truth faſt, therefore the Apoſtle bids us to be glued unto it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 9. it is with truths
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> as with ſome plants which live and thrive not, but in warme climates.</p>
            <p>That ancient deſire after truth and delight in it, to take counſell from it, and ſtrength from it, and comfort by it, muſt not decay and dye within us, but muſt remaine and abound, though others hate, diſgrace, and endeavour to make voyd the truth, yet wee muſt cleave unto it, and love it, as <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 119.</p>
            <p n="3">3 In our profeſſion; hence that advice of the Apoſtle in <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 16
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:17566:115"/> 
               <hi>to hold forth the word of life, even in the midſt of a darke and froward generation:</hi> Chriſt would have us not onely to beleeve, but to confeſſe him before men. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that it was no ſmall ſinne in <hi>Peter,</hi> when he preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that he knew not the man. <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> reports in one of his orations againſt <hi>Iuli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> that ſome Chriſtian ſouldiers being cunningly circumvented by him to idolatrous ſacrifices, perceiving the errour, they all ran backe unto him, and threw him his money againe, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted they were Chriſtians, and in what they did, they were circumvented by him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 23.</note> 23. <hi>let us hold faſt the profeſsion of
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:17566:115"/> our faith without wavering;</hi> the Chriſtian muſt change neither his Maſter, nor his ſervice, nor his livery.</p>
            <p n="4">4 In our converſation; wee muſt ſtill practiſe truths, and keepe our lives anſwerable unto them. Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> cals this a wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in the truth: then a man walkes in the truth, when hee holds on his courſe of holy obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience unto it, againſt all the encouragements and diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements of the world, as the three children in <hi>Daniel,</hi> &amp;c. not with the Galathians begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the ſpirit, and ending in the fleſh, or like thoſe Iſraelites, whoſe righteouſneſſe was as the morning dew. But we muſt
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:17566:116"/> ſtill runne the race ſet before us, and keep ſtedfaſt our feet unto the pathes of righteouſneſſe and waies of truth.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>Why must divine truths heard and received be held faſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> Reaſons thereof are many, I will briefly point out ſome of them.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Divine truth is a moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and excellent thing, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in Scripture it is compared to gold, which of metals is the moſt precious, nay it is more precious then gold or rubies, and all the things which thou canſt deſire, are not to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared unto it, ſee <hi>Pro.</hi> 3. 14. 15. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 3. 14. 15.</note> It is more excellent then the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies of the creatures, not
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:17566:116"/> then ſome of them, but then all of them; and a man if hee were to imagine any excellency, or if the utmoſt of his deſires were enlarged, yet could they not finde out and pitch upon ſuch an excellency. Therefore ſaith Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> to the Church of <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladelphia, Revel. 3. 11. Hold that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Revel.</hi> 3. 11.</note> 
               <hi>faſt which thou haſt, that no man take thy crowne;</hi> the crowne is the top of royalties, ſuch a thing is truth, let no man take thy crowne.</p>
            <p>Beloved, there are two pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties which aſſure us of the excellency of things.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The more holy they are, the <note place="margin">Two things intimate an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency.</note> more excellent they are; all cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions are diminutions of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency,
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:17566:117"/> the more mixt a thing is, the more it is abaſed, as if gold and tinne be mixed; and the more pure it is, as meere gold, the more glorious it is. Now the truths of God are holy, not as perſons are holy (which is with mixture and imperfection) but as the light at noone day is pure without darkeneſſe at all.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The more that God is in any thing, the more excellent it is, for ſo much as we partake of him (who is excellency it ſelfe) ſo much more wee riſe in our excellency.</p>
            <p>But the great God is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeen in this word of truth: there is his wiſedome, there is his power and greatneſſe, there
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:17566:117"/> is his love and mercifulneſſe, there is his Chriſt and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, therefore it is moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and conſequently to be held faſt by us.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Divine truths are (as it were) made over to us under termes of conſtancy and perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity: I finde in Scriptures that they are termed ſometimes</p>
            <p>Our heritage; eſtates which are perſonall (if that bee the phraſe) for poſſeſſion may be ſold, as that which a childe buyes with his owne money; but eſtates which are naturall or hereditary, ſuch I meane as come to be ours by deſcent, theſe ought to be kept for poſterity: God forbid ſaid <hi>Naboth,</hi> that I
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:17566:118"/> ſhould ſell the inheritance of my fathers: divine truths are an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritage to deſcend from us to our children, and therefore wee are neither to diſpoſſeſſe our ſelves of them, nor to ſuffer our ſelves by any to bee diſpoſſeſſed of them, <hi>Pſal. 119. 111. thy teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119 111.</note> 
               <hi>have I taken as an heritage for euer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Gods truſt: ſomething wee commit to God, ſomething God commits to us, 2 <hi>Tim. 1. 12. He is able to keepe that which I haue committed unto him:</hi> we truſt God with our ſoules, and God truſts us with his truths, which are therefore called, that good thing committed to us for to keep, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 14. now in matters
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:17566:118"/> of truſt, wee muſt be faithfull, for we muſt be reſponſable for the whole wherewith wee are inſtructed, as the ſervants in the Goſpell, who had talents com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to their truſt, they were called to an account for them: ſo if the Lord truſt any man with graces, or with his truths, the man muſt carefully keepe and preſerve them, for the Lord will aske him another day for his truſt, as Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> did of the Biſhop of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> for his <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They obſerve that a truſt muſt be, firſt, redelivered, ſecondly, wholly, thirdly, onely to him who committed it to us for truſt.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="222" facs="tcp:17566:119"/>3 Not to hold faſt the truths, is an exceeding and fearefull in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury or wrong, it is injurious,</p>
            <p n="1">1 To God, for he is the Lord or God of truth: truths are ours for the efficacie of them, but onely this for the authority of them. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> Should a private perſon preſume of himſelfe to ſell the Kings Iewels? it might bee as much as his life is worth: truths are Gods Iewels, hee reveales them, he ownes them, hee hath ſealed them with the bloud of Chriſt, and therefore thou doeſt preſumptuouſly wrong the Lord to put off the things which belong to him.</p>
            <p n="2">2 To our covenant and vow, what was our baptiſme but a
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:17566:119"/> devoting and ſolemne vowing of our ſelves to be faithfull to Chriſt and to his truths? wee ſolemnly profeſſed that none ſhould be our Lord, but God, and that we ſhould be his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſervants unto our lives end, yea and wee have ratified this vow many a time, by comming to the Sacrament of the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>Now if we doe not hold faſt the truths of Chriſt, but forſake them or any of them, wee are guilty of extreame perjury, not in a matter betwixt man and man, but betwixt God and man; thou art forſworne again and againe unto the Lord thy God, and haſt (as much as in
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:17566:120"/> thee lies) made voyd the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of grace and life for thy poore ſoule.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Conſider but the neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry uſes of divine truths, and then we will acknowledge that they are to be held faſt.</p>
            <p>The uſe of the word or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine truths, reſpects the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting and happy condition of the ſoule, from the beginning to the end thereof. Everlaſting and true happineſſe is the end and ſcope that every Chriſtian lookes at; and divine truths ſerve him fully and effectually, to this end, both to diſcover it, and to bring man unto it.</p>
            <p>There are many things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to ſet us in the true way,
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:17566:120"/> to bring a man to heaven, <hi>v. g.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 Conviction of his ſinfull condition, but the word in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightens the minde, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinceth the conſcience.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Contrition for ſinne, but the word pricks our hearts, as <hi>Acts</hi> 2. and humbles them.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Converſion of ſoule; but the law of the Lord is perfect, converting the ſoule, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. 7. by it comes faith into the ſoule, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. 7.</note> which gets Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 17. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 17.</note> by it comes repentance, <hi>Acts</hi> 3. 19.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Augmentation of grace; but by the word wee are built up, <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 32. and grow more and more.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Perſeverance in grace; but
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:17566:121"/> by the word wee are kept and eſtabliſhed to the end, it is the power of God unto ſalvation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 16. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 16.</note>
            </p>
            <p>What ſhould I ſay more, reade the Apoſtle ſumming up all in 2 <hi>Tim. 3. 16. All Scripture is giuen</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 16.</note> 
               <hi>by inſpiration of God, and is profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for doctrine, for reproofe, for correction, for inſtruction in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>17 <hi>That the man of God may be perfect, throughly furniſhed to all good workes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>15 <hi>Yea they are able to make us wiſe unto ſaluation, through faith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hich is in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, there are many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements comforting and ſupporting in our way, as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine conſolations of the ſpirit
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:17566:121"/> of God, peace in conſcience joy in the holy Ghoſt, all which are the myrrhe dropping onely from divine truths; thy word hath comforted me, ſaid <hi>Dauid,</hi> thy word hath quickned mee; in the houſe of my pilgrimage, they were the joyes of his heart, and in the daies of his calamity they were the ſtay of his heart.</p>
            <p>Now put all together, if di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine truths ſhew us the true happineſſe, if they onely put us into the true way, unto that true happineſſe, if they onely keepe us in that way, if they onely comfort and ſtrengthen us in that way, if they onely bring us to the end of our faith, even the ſalvation of our
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:17566:122"/> ſoules, will we not, ought wee not to hold them faſt?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> The firſt uſe of this point ſhall be to convince and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the wonderfull incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy of the ſonnes of men, that ſlipperineſſe and unſetled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſpirit, which is to be found amongſt them.</p>
            <p>Conſider divine truths as they lye.</p>
            <p n="1">1 In doctrine; we may now complaine as the Apoſtle did of the Galathians, chap. 1. verſe 6. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 6.</note> 
               <hi>I maruell that ye are ſo ſoone remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from him that called you into the grace of Chriſt, unto another Goſpell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some revolt from the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant doctrine, to the Popiſh
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:17566:122"/> leven, others fall off from the orthodoxe articles of our Church, to Anabaptiſticall fancies, and Socinian Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and the Lord be mercifull unto us, what daily unſetled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and giddineſſe poſſeſſeth us; if any novelty of doctrine (though a root of bitterneſſe) ſtart up and be delivered with any confidence or cunning of deceiving wit, how inſtantly we flye off from our old truths, how greedily and madly wee ſucke in poyſonous errours, and being thus driven with every winde, what tempeſts of railing and diſgraces doe wee heape upon thoſe who croſſe our fickleneſſe with conſtant
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:17566:123"/> vindications and aſſertings of the true doctrines of faith and life.</p>
            <p>It makes mee to pitty this great and famous City, whiles I behold a <hi>colluvies,</hi> a very rabble of all opinions, and ſuch a going and comming, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings at, and ſaylings off from the land of uprightneſſe: One weeke this is a truth, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt an article; the next weeke it is no ſuch matter, but ſome other thing is the right.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> Thus wee play many times with great truths, as children doe with their Babies, one while embrace them, anone breake them and throw them into the dirt.</p>
            <pb n="231" facs="tcp:17566:123"/>
            <p>But are there ſo many waies to heaven as men will make, or haſt thou power to coine other articles of faith at pleaſure, or will the Lord beare all this reſting and mocking with his truths? Two things makes mee feare the Lord will puniſh us in the Goſpell; one is, our generall barrenneſſe in life, another is our great ſickleneſſe in matter of truths.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In converſation; many times we hold the truth in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe: wee doe not prize the truth and love it, nor live according to it with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, but as the Prophet cryed out, <hi>how is the beautifull City be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come an heape?</hi> ſo may wee ſay of
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:17566:124"/> many, how is their righteous walkings degenerated into an ungodly living? their wine is ſowred, and lamp put out.</p>
            <p>But I will tell you the reaſons and cauſes of all this inconſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy <note place="margin">The cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of conſtanc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>y.</note> and apoſtacy, <hi>v. g.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 Men are very ignorant, and therefore very inconſtant: ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance is the great ſpunge to ſucke in errours, as pride is the great Bawd to vent them. Chaffe may be toſſed any way: that which is weak, is alſo light.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Though their apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons be large, yet their affections are foule, they know truth, but love ſinne which is contrary to truth: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> now a foule ſtomacke ever makes an ill head, and a
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:17566:124"/> ſecret love of ſinne, works out the ſtrength of truth in the minde: men doe the more eaſily grow erroneous, who firſt grow irreligious.</p>
            <p n="3">3 There is an itch of pride; <hi>Evah</hi> and <hi>Adam</hi> would know more then was fit, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore loſt all that was good; you never reade of a proud perſon, but either his life was notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly tainted, or his judgement notably corrupted: the greateſt errours, have fallen from thoſe that have beene moſt proud, and have beene tooke up by thoſe that have beene moſt ignorant.</p>
            <p n="4">4 And then alſo many have <hi>Athenian wits,</hi> they long for <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velties,</hi>
               <pb n="234" facs="tcp:17566:125"/> though the old wine be beſt, yet their palate muſt be in the faſhion for new; there is a ſore vanity in a naturall minde, that it cannot long fixe on any eſtate, or on any truth.</p>
            <p n="5">5 A colloging ſlaviſhneſſe, many give up their ſoules and faith to the religion of others, and like waxe, are ſtill faſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the opinions of great perſons; they are afraid of their diſpleaſures, and therefore even in points of religion, will dance after their pipe.</p>
            <p n="6">6 A ſordid and eminent love of the world, for which <hi>Demas</hi> forſooke Chriſt, and <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> ſold his Maſter, and <hi>Hyme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus</hi> made ſhipwracke of faith:
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:17566:125"/> the unſatisfiable ſlave to the world will never be a faithfull ſervant to truth; hee who hath already pawnd his ſoule, will with as much eaſe ſell off the truth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Spira</hi> for its ſake abjured the truth, but ventured the loſſe of it, and himſelfe too.</p>
            <p n="7">7 Many men are licentious, and therefore unſtedfaſt: cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt doctrines give more ſcope then the true and heavenly: wee are apt to beleeve that ſooneſt, which pleaſeth us moſt; errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous points are more for plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and divine truths are more for ſtrictneſſe, and <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> therefore as thoſe Grecians (if I forget not the ſtory) gave up their wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:17566:126"/> to enjoy their ſports, ſo many give up the truth, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy their eaſie and looſe kinde of walking.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> But for you, I hope better things, though I thus ſpeake: hitherto you have heard the good truths and waies of God, and have held them faſt, I have not found you (as other people) of ſo unſetled and inconſtant ſpirits. And therefore as Chriſt ſaid to the Church of <hi>Thyatira,</hi> the ſame I will preſume to ſay unto you, <hi>Revel.</hi> 2. 24. 25. I will <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 24. 25.</note> put upon you no other burden but that which ye have already, <hi>holdfaſt:</hi> what need I urge this with many motives?</p>
            <p n="1">1 If it be truth, why ſhould it <note place="margin">Motives.</note>
               <pb n="237" facs="tcp:17566:126"/> be left? is errour better then truth? then ſhould darkeneſſe be better then light?</p>
            <p n="2">2 Can you better your eſtates by leaving of truths? when the divels fell from truth, they fell from heaven, when <hi>Adam</hi> fell from truth, hee fell from Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Will not the truth keepe you? if you keepe the truth as the ſhip doth the Pilot who keepeth it, truth will keepe thy ſoule and graces together, thy ſoule and Chriſt together, thy ſoule and comfort together, thy ſoule and proſperity together, therefore it is called the girdle of truth, becauſe as a girdle it holds all together. Thou parteſt with
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:17566:127"/> ſtrength, with joy, with ſafety, with bleſſing, with happineſſe if thou part with truth.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The reward is ſure, if thou be faithfull, not a meane re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, but that of life, even a crowne of life, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 10. <note place="margin">Rev. 2. 10. Rules.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now that you may for ever hold faſt divine truths, take theſe rules or directions.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Lay a ſolid foundation in diſtinct knowledge of them; confuſed braines cauſe unſetled hearts: reſt not in <hi>Pilates</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand what is truth, nor in the Iſraelites hovering betwixt two opinions, nor in that groſſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary of religion, to take up truth upon truſt, for any man ſake whatſoever, were he the ſharpeſt
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:17566:127"/> 
               <hi>Ieremiah,</hi> or the learnedſt <hi>Paul,</hi> or the comfortableſt <hi>Barnabas;</hi> be not ſatisfied this is truth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this, that man ſaith, but as the honourable Beraeans ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Scriptures about the things which even Saint <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe delivered, ſo doe you prove all things ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, receive truth upon an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of truth, if the firſt truth (which is the word of God) and the rule and compaſſe will not approve it, it is errour and not truth.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>Yea, but how may wee know truths, for there are many religions, and many opinions obtruded to the world, the truth of which cannot ſo or ſily be diſcerned.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="240" facs="tcp:17566:128"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> I anſwer, that true do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine may be diſcerned from falſe doctrines, 1 by the <hi>unity</hi> of them, <hi>unum &amp; verum convertun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> truth is one or none, there is but one way (ſaith <hi>Ariſtotle)</hi> to hit the marke, but many waies to miſſe it; errour is manifold and divers, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> like the image which <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> ſaw mixt of gold and clay, and as <hi>Aristotle</hi> ſpeakes of Vices, that they are contrary both to vertues and themſelves; ſo erroneous do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines are oppoſite to truth, and to themſelves; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> there is no errour but is like a lyer, apt to forget and wound it ſelfe, but truth is ſingle, like Chriſts gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, undivided; as there is but
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:17566:128"/> one Chriſt, ſo but one faith.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The purity of them; all falſe doctrine (like treacherous phyſicke) gives eaſe;
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> or like a whore, much in beauty, when falſe in honeſty: what it wants in verity, it makes up in liberty; like ill wares which therefore have the larger allowances; the doctrine which is unſound, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally is licentious, as is evident in the <hi>Mahometan</hi> or <hi>Popiſh</hi> te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents.</p>
            <p>But truth is holy in it ſelfe, and to us, teaching it within the heart, and ordering it in the life. It is an adverſary to ſin, becauſe all ſin is an adverſary unto God.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The efficacy of them: uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally corrupt doctrines adde to
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:17566:129"/> our notions, but meddle not with our corruptions; they ſwell us, but doe not edifie us, they are pils which onely worke upon the braine, they neither bring true grace, or ſound peace with them: onely this, Satan makes the erroneous very violent, that thereby they may thinke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the right.</p>
            <p>But the doctrine which is true, is ſtrong, it is heavenly in its na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and mighty in its operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, comes from God, and brings to God, makes the bad good, and the good better; there is no ſuch ſalve to heale a corrupt heart, nor balme to refreſh a troubled conſcience, as truth.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The antiquity of them:
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:17566:129"/> errour is but the ſhadow and ape of truth, the ſaying is, <hi>id demúm veriſsimum quod antiquiſsimum.</hi> Truth is the firſt borne, for God ſpake it, before the divell ſpake the other; errors may be old, but truth ſaw the light before them; the whole <hi>farrago</hi> of corrupt do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines amongſt the Papiſts for tranſubſtantiation, invocation of Saints, prayers for the dead, merit, ſupremacy; their originals were of yeſterday; though they boaſt antiquity, yet they dare not ſtand to the triall of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, who muſt decide all truths.</p>
            <p n="5">5 The ſimplicity of them: errours came in by the Serpent at the firſt, and are much of its
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:17566:130"/> nature, full of windings and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings; all corrupt doctrines are deceiveable and ſubtile: how many arts were fained by <hi>Arrius</hi> and the Arrian Biſhops, to bring in their damnable errour? what forging of lyes, and odious accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> that he was diſhoneſt with a woman, and cut off a mans hand, as <hi>Euſebius</hi> relates: and ſo the Ieſuites about <hi>Calvin,</hi> and <hi>Luther,</hi> and <hi>Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cthon,</hi> and <hi>Beza,</hi> &amp;c. and ſo for the eſtabliſhing of the Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> the Popes Cloke-bags were weekely filled with devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and carriages.</p>
            <p>Yea, and obſerve the very Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts at this day, how deceivea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly confident they are, that al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="245" facs="tcp:17566:130"/> antiquity and teſtimony is on their ſide, when either it is a packe of their owne writers onely, or other authors which they have forged, or elſe antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty miſerably lanced and cut, and interlaced by their <hi>Index expur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorius:</hi> yea, and I pray God that many of the opinions in this City be not bolſtered up with high clamours, and with artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall lyes. But truth is naked and plaine, it is neither of a cruell na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, like <hi>Caine,</hi> nor of a ſubtile ſpirit with <hi>Abſalom,</hi> nor of a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpirit with <hi>Ahabs</hi> falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, it flatters no man, nor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiles any: being truth, it is not aſhamed of light or triall, and it alone can maintain it ſelf againſt
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:17566:131"/> all contrary quarrels: a good cauſe is like a good conſcience, even a bulwarke to it ſelfe, like the ſunne in its light, and heat againſt all clouds, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>5 The duration of them: truth like the ſunne hath runne down through all ages: not that all men have embraced it, but that by ſome it hath ſtill beene embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced: ſome one or more hath ſtill beene at the barre, to beare wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe unto it. New men have ſtill riſen up, (and ſometimes out of the aſhes as it were of the dead) to maintaine, and either by tongue, or pen, or bloud, to defend the truth: but</p>
            <p>Erroneous doctrines, as they want an inward harmony, ſo
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:17566:131"/> alſo an outward conſent, like a deceitfull brooke, they are ſpent after a while, or like commoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in a ſtate, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> though ſtrong or long, yet they come to an end at length, either ſome ſpeciall judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments on the ringleaders, or the authority of Princes, as <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> againſt <hi>Arius,</hi> or the prayers of the Saints, or the deciſion of lawfull counſels have ſtill ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiered theſe meteors: but as it is ſaid of divine mercy, that it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dures for ever, the ſame is affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of divine truth, it runs from one generation to another; till Chriſt make his Church tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant, the militant Church ſhall be the pillar of truth.</p>
            <p>6 The conformity of them
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:17566:132"/> to the rule or word. Erroneous doctrines like unſound fleſh, cannot abide handling, and <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> like an ill favoured woman, would have all glaſſes broken.</p>
            <p>But truth like ſound gold, will endure a touch-ſtone, truth will be found truth upon ſearch, bring it to the conſcience, it will worke as truth; bring it to the death-bed, it will uphold as truth; bring it to the ſcriptures, it will hold out as truth.</p>
            <p>2 When truths upon ſearch are found to be truths, then em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace them for the truths ſake, not upon perſonall and mutable cauſes or ends.</p>
            <p>3 Firme refolution after try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, by which our knowledge
<pb n="249" facs="tcp:17566:132"/> comes to be cleare, and without doubt there muſt be now a plain reſolution and purpoſe of heart in cleaving to ſuch faithfully e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videnced truths: thou muſt by an immoveable faith (as it were) root thy very heart in the truths of Chriſt, as Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> though bonds and afflictions, though good report or evill, though death it ſelfe abide him for Chriſt, come what will come, diſputes, fancies, errors, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, loſſes, I have found the truth, and it will I hold for ever.</p>
            <p>3 Loyall affection: then it is loyall, when it is incluſive, to every truth, &amp;c. excluſive to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but truth: this loyall affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:17566:133"/> will make us to, firſt, doe, ſecondly, ſuffer, thirdly, cleave: love truth, and then truth will be held: I held him, and would not let him goe, ſaid the Church, then in love with Chriſt, <hi>Cant.</hi> 3. Love is the eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt key to open the heart to
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.</note> Chriſt, and the ſtrongeſt locke to keepe ſure the truth in our hearts: when thou haſt experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally felt the heavenly ſtrength and comfort of Gods truths, then wilt thou certainly ſticke unto them.</p>
            <p>4 Ioyne conſcience to ſcience: O when people have the truths ſtill ſounding in their eares, and ungodlineſſe ſtill ſtirring and ruling in their lives, it cannot
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:17566:133"/> be, that they ſhould have ſtrong hands, who have wicked hearts; <hi>Hymeneus</hi> made ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke of faith, and of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence both together, 1 <hi>Tim</hi> 1. 19.</p>
            <p>Therefore ſtrive to obey the <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 19.</note> truths, adde to thy faith vertue; be a doing Chriſtian as well as a knowing Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>5 Be watchfull in prayer to God, with <hi>David,</hi> to uphold thee, with Saint <hi>Peter</hi> to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh thee, ſtill to keepe thee, that thou mayeſt keepe his truths: excellent is that ſpeech of <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">S. Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard. in Pſal. qui habitat pag. 283. Baſil.</note> 
               <hi>neque enim quae habemus ab eo, ſervare aut tenere poſsumus ſine eo;</hi> that God by whoſe light a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone we know the truth, by his ſtrength alone we keepe it.</p>
            <pb n="252" facs="tcp:17566:134"/>
            <p>Thus much for the text, and now for the occaſion, and here I cannot be long, neither my af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections nor yours will admit of large diſcourſe, onely a word of you, and a word to you.</p>
            <p>Of you, ſo regardfull have you beene to my Miniſtery, ſo loving to my perſon, ſo faithfull in your maintenance, ſo cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully encouraging generally from you all, but chiefly from the chiefeſt, that had it pleaſed the Lord to have given mee health (the which I have ſcarce enjoyed one whole yeere toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſince I have beene heere) I ſhould not have ſtirred eaſily from ſuch a people, for the beſt preferment that could be conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently
<pb n="253" facs="tcp:17566:134"/> offered unto me.</p>
            <p>I ſpeake my heart freely, I cannot tell on which ſide the unwillingneſſe is moſt, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on your part who are left, or on my part who am conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to leave you.</p>
            <p>But to ſay no more of your goodneſſe, give mee leave (for the cloſe of all) to leave a few Legacies with you, being all my friends, and hearken to my words, as the words of a dying man, for the Lord knowes how ſhort my daies may be.</p>
            <p>My Legacies are theſe:</p>
            <p n="1">1 Lay out more time for your ſoules: the ſoule is a precious thing, the ſoule is a corrupted thing, ſinnes are in it, much
<pb n="254" facs="tcp:17566:135"/> guilt is upon it, there is a Chriſt that it needs, holineſſe that it muſt have, heaven that it would have, thy body is but clay, thy ſoule a ſpirit, the world a vanity, thy ſoule im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall: all is well if the ſoule be wel, nothing is well if that be evill: I beſeech you pray more, heare more, know more, confer more, doe more and more for your ſoules, when you come to dye, you will then finde it to be all your worke: O then whiles health is in you, make it thy chiefeſt worke to ſeeke the kingdome of heaven and the righteouſneſſe thereof for your ſoules, feed not the ſlave, and ſtarve the childe.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="255" facs="tcp:17566:135"/>2 Vpon good grounds make ſure of a reconciled God: live not in an unreconciled conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: no enemy like an ill conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and a good God: ſtudy the right of thy ſinnes, and the bloud of Chriſt, repentance from dead workes, and faith in the Lord Ieſus, ſo ſhalt thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the face of God and live. The waies of reconciliation with God, and the ſetling of thy conſcience about it, may coſt thee many prayers and teares, and diligent ſtudies, but the love of God and heaven will anſwer, and recompenſe all.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Wiſely improve all heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeaſons: the Lord hitherto hath continued unto you, daies
<pb n="256" facs="tcp:17566:136"/> of peace and ſalvation, heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly opportunities publike and private, and I beſeech him for ever ſo to doe. Now receive not the grace of God in vaine, lay hold on theſe occaſions, if there be not wiſedome to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove them, there may be ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for neglecting them. You ſee how many worthy and faithfull Miniſters God hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away (of late) by death, and ſhall the preſent Prophets live for ever? O then in your day and time hearken, regard, repent, beleeve, live, and thrive under holy and faithfull Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, make more uſe of their doctrines, of their rules, of their counſels, of their comforts, of
<pb n="257" facs="tcp:17566:136"/> their experience and prayers, the night will come when neither we nor you muſt worke any longer.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Study the grounds and principles of religion better; firſt, lay good foundations, and then build on them: errours in the entrance, weaken all in the progreſſe. Take paines to know what that good and acceptable will of the Lord is: a well bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomed Chriſtian is like a well-bottomed veſſell at ſea, which can ride out in all weathers: no Chriſtian ſtands ſo faſt, or thrives ſo well as the well groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Chriſtian.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Be rather an agent, then a diſputant in religion? the vanity
<pb n="258" facs="tcp:17566:137"/> of wit is to argue much, but the ſincerity of the heart is to doe much: for doubtfull points, and ſubtile novelties, let others beat them, and ſerve them, and in the meane while, pray thou much, that thou mayeſt obey the truths which thou kno weſt. In ſpeculatives be wiſe to ſobri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, in practicals be as good as thou canſt: it is not the wittieſt ſcholler, but the trueſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an who ſhall goe to heaven.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Be leſſe formall, and more fruitfull: know that as we muſt be brought to an account for every word which we ſpeake, ſo much more for every word that God ſpeakes.</p>
            <p>Meere godlineſſe is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
<pb n="259" facs="tcp:17566:137"/> under conſtant and great meanes of grace: God expects much when he gives much: if it doth not utterly caſt thee, yet it muſt exceſſively trouble thee to be thin in bearing, when God hath been large in ſowing.</p>
            <p n="7">7 Let all Chriſtians bee of more fruitfull hearts and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſpirits one towards ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. There are treacherous and malitious hearts enough in the world, thou needeſt not to helpe the divell to be an accuſer of the brethren. It is a ſad thing when one Chriſtian can hardly truſt another, and that they who ſhould pitty and heale in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, are yet inventers of lies and obloquies; theſe are the
<pb n="260" facs="tcp:17566:138"/> wounds which my friends gave me, ſaid the Church in the <hi>Canticles.</hi> If thy fellow Chriſtian doe faile, rather compaſſionate and ſuccour him, then hate and reproach him; thou ſhalt never eſtabliſh thy graces or name upon the ruines and ſcandals of another man; if thou be a ſtrong Chriſtian, be more tender, if weake, be more ſilent; the ſtrong ſhould beare the infirmities of the weake, and the weake ſhould hearken to the directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the ſtrong: your graces are ſtrong, and ſafety ſurer by love then by diviſion, therefore be of one minde, and live in peace, let brotherly love con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <pb n="261" facs="tcp:17566:138"/>8 Minde death often, and prepare for it betimes; hee who is a ſtranger to dying thoughts, is ordinarily a ſtranger to a godly life; thou wouldeſt haſten and better thy worke, if thou didſt more looke backe on thy life, and more forward on thy death.</p>
            <p n="9">9 Be diligent in your parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular places: the idle body can hardly hold a good ſoule; that man is in danger, who is all for heaven, or all for earth, both our callings muſt be regarded.</p>
            <p n="10">10 Be much in praier: the Chriſtian uſually gets the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt bleſſings on his knees; God is much with him in grace, who is moſt with God in praier.</p>
            <pb n="262" facs="tcp:17566:139"/>
            <p>And pray not for your ſelves onely, but for others, and as for others, ſo for me, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> deſired of the Epheſians, <hi>c.</hi> 6. 19. that utterance may be given un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mee, that I may open my mouth boldly to make knowne the myſtery of the Goſpell, that therein <hi>(v.</hi> 20.) I may ſpeake as I ought to ſpeake; and ſo as the ſame Apoſtle in his <hi>ultimum vale</hi> ſaid to thoſe Epheſians, the ſame I ſay unto you.</p>
            <p>Brethren, I commend you unto God, and to the word of his grace, which is able to build you up, and to give you an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance amongſt all them which are ſanctified.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="index">
            <pb facs="tcp:17566:139"/>
            <head>The Table.</head>
            <list>
               <head>A</head>
               <item>ACtivity of love to ſet on graces, p 144</item>
               <item>Affections are many times dying, p. 11. 45</item>
               <item>Ardency of affections, an exceeding helpe, 1 to the remembrance of truths taught, 2 to the holding faſt of the truth, p 198. &amp; 213</item>
               <item>The different carriage of a weakened and a ſtrengthened Christian under afflictions p 111,</item>
               <item>The application of Chriſt, the ordinances and other meanes helpefull againſt decaying, p 72. 98. 131</item>
               <item>Apoſtaſie from the truth, ſeven cauſes of it, p 272</item>
               <item>Gods approbation to be ſtudied, p 158</item>
               <item>A diſtinct apprehenſion of truths needfull to the remembrance of truths, p 200</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>C</head>
               <item>CAuſes of a dying condition, p 16</item>
               <item>Chriſt ſtrengthens a languiſhing Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian three waies, p 79</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:17566:140"/>
               <item>Comforts attend Chriſtians, and when? p 40</item>
               <item>Communion with God, and its kindes, p 38. 39</item>
               <item>Conference about truths taught, uſefull, p 201</item>
               <item>Conſcience to be joyned with ſcience; p 250</item>
               <item>Conſcience wounded and vexed, p. 16. 40</item>
               <item>Corruptions have a decaying power, p 16</item>
               <item>Conſiderations of a mans condition is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, p 121</item>
               <item>A dying converſation, p. 10. 50</item>
               <item>Truths taught to be kept in a mans converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. p 215</item>
               <item>Lively conſociation, what? p 135</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>D</head>
               <item>DAmping of communion with God. p 38</item>
               <item>Depresſion of heavenly ſtrength, p 36</item>
               <item>Delight taken in godly company, p 108</item>
               <item>Delightfulneſse in love, p 145</item>
               <item>Diligence in love, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>True doctrines diſcovered from falſe in ſeven things, p 240</item>
               <item>Seven diſadvantages in a weakened condition, p 92</item>
               <item>Deſertion a conſequent of decaying, p 40</item>
               <item>A dying diſpoſition opened, p 8</item>
               <item>Chriſtians are dying in ſeven reſpects, p 10</item>
               <item>Dying in duties how knowne, p 44 53</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>E</head>
               <item>EXamination neglected, the evill of it, p 22. 23</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:17566:140"/>
               <item>Exceſse in pasſion dangerous, p 28</item>
               <item>Excellency hath two things in it, p 217</item>
               <item>Expresſions of grace, 1 paſſionate, 2 delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, p 63</item>
               <item>Extenuatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of excellencies by decayings, p 34</item>
               <item>Truths are to be embraced, p 248</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>F</head>
               <item>FAintneſse in acts of religion, p 53</item>
               <item>Faith a radicall and ſtrengthening grace, p 14. 142</item>
               <item>Forgetfulneſse of the word evill and hurtfull, p 190</item>
               <item>Formality to be checked. p 69</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>G</head>
               <item>MEn may decay in gifts and graces, and how? p 13, 14</item>
               <item>Graces given to men for three ends, p 54</item>
               <item>Graces are inclining, inlarging and cleanſing principles, p 55, 56, 57</item>
               <item>Graces beſtowed, are to be kept in repaire<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> p 88</item>
               <item>Graces diffuſed, and graces imployed, how to be underſtood, p 64</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>H</head>
               <item>HEaring not enough for a Chriſtian, p 187</item>
               <item>A plaine and a pliable heart, p 132</item>
               <item>Helpes, firſt, to remember, ſecondly, to hold faſt truths, p 198. 238</item>
               <item>Hold faſt the truth, p 210</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:17566:141"/>
               <item>Divine truths a Chriſtians heritage, p 219</item>
               <item>Humbling under decayings, p 67</item>
               <item>Deep humiliation a meanes to ſtrengthen a decayed Chriſtian, p 123</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>I</head>
               <item>IEalouſie and three things ariſing from it, p 70</item>
               <item>Inconſtancy and its cauſes, p 232</item>
               <item>Implantation of holy principles, what it is? p 74</item>
               <item>Interruption in duties, p 64</item>
               <item>Decaies in judgement. p 12</item>
               <item>The imperfection of our eſtate before God, p 157</item>
               <item>Truths held faſt in judgement, p 211</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>L</head>
               <item>THree things in love furthering duties, p 144, 145</item>
               <item>Loyall affection to the truth, p 299</item>
               <item>Ten legacies, p 253</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>M</head>
               <item>MEditation an helpe to memory, p 199</item>
               <item>Meanes to keepe up graces, p 67</item>
               <item>Meanes to recover out of a dying condition, p 73</item>
               <item>Meanes of ſtrengthening, p 121</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>N</head>
               <item>NEglect and its danger, p 19</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:17566:141"/>
               <head>O</head>
               <item>COnſtant operation, what? p 200</item>
               <item>Oppoſition againſt dying cauſes, p 137</item>
               <item>Ordinances, and three things about them, 97</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>P</head>
               <item>THree ſorts of people living under the meanes, p 7</item>
               <item>Perfection and a ſtriving unto it, p 68</item>
               <item>Perfecting of holy principles, p 75</item>
               <item>Perſiſtance in holy truths, p 202</item>
               <item>Practiſe a keeper of truths, p 202</item>
               <item>Practicall remembrance, what it is, p 167</item>
               <item>Practicall truths what they are, p 175</item>
               <item>Preparation to the ordinances, p 97</item>
               <item>Phyſicking the ſoule, what? p 22</item>
               <item>Dying in profeſſion, what, p 10</item>
               <item>Truth is held by profeſſion, p 214</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>R</head>
               <item>REaſons for the ſtrengthening of a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall condition, p 84</item>
               <item>Reaſons to hold faſt divine truths, p 216</item>
               <item>Active reformation, what, p 128</item>
               <item>Truths taught are to be remembred, p 163</item>
               <item>The nature, ſorts, waies, cauſes, and meanes of rememembrance, p 160. to 202</item>
               <item>Reſiſtance of ſinne, p 102</item>
               <item>Riſing of graces, p 110</item>
               <item>Solid reſolutions, p 125</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:17566:142"/>
               <item>Reſolution to cleave to the truth, p 249</item>
               <item>Revolting from doctrine, p 228. and in converſation, 231</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>S</head>
               <item>SIlence in heaven, what and when, p 41</item>
               <item>Sin, and a Chriſtian in ſinning, p 60, 61</item>
               <item>Seriouſneſſe in ſociety, p 71</item>
               <item>Standing at a ſtay, p 70</item>
               <item>Strengthening of ſpirituals under decayes, p 74. 78. 83</item>
               <item>Supplication muſt be ardent, p 129</item>
               <item>Suſpition of a mans owne condition, p 42</item>
               <item>Sen ſibleneſse and ſpiritualneſse not equall, p 62</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>T</head>
               <item>TImes of ſpirituall troubles<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> p 41</item>
               <item>Truths add their ſorts, p 175, 205, 206</item>
               <item>Divine truths is Gods truſt, p 220</item>
               <item>Three things about a truſt. p 221</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Z</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>A</hi> Caſe reſolved about decayings in zeale, p 62</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:17566:142"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PAge 8. line 16. for <hi>a,</hi> reade <hi>ſecondly,</hi> p. 147. l. 3. for <hi>wit,</hi> r. <hi>we all know, &amp;c.</hi> p. 221. l. 4. for <hi>inſtructed,</hi> r. <hi>intrusted.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Octob.</hi> 22. 1639.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p> Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>IOH. HANSLEY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
